<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons warning by Laodicea's luke-warmnesse. Or A sermon preached at Paules-crosse, the 10. of October, 1613 Being the first Sunday in tearme. By Sampson Price, Mr. of Arts, of Exeter-Colledge; and preacher to the cittie of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112001</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847260</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847260</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1580:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons warning by Laodicea's luke-warmnesse. Or A sermon preached at Paules-crosse, the 10. of October, 1613 Being the first Sunday in tearme. By Sampson Price, Mr. of Arts, of Exeter-Colledge; and preacher to the cittie of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Snodham] for Iohn Barnes, dwelling on Snoe-hill, at the signe of the Harrow,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12287:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDONS</hi> WARNING BY <hi>Laodicea's</hi> Luke-warmneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR</hi> A SERMON Preached at <hi>Paules-Croſſe,</hi> the 10. of <hi>October,</hi> 1613. BEING <hi>The firſt Sunday in Tearme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY SAMPSON PRICE, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of <hi>Arts,</hi> of <hi>Exeter-Colledge;</hi> and Preacher to the Cittie of OXFORD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Barnes,</hi> dwelling on Snoe-hill, at the ſigne of the Harrow, 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12287:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12287:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHTLY <hi>HONORABLE,</hi> AND right <hi>Reuerend</hi> Father in God, IOHN, by diuine <hi>Prouidence,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat your <hi>Honour</hi> commanded, I haue <hi>performed,</hi> as God <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled.</hi> This <hi>Sermon</hi> which by your <hi>powerfull</hi> Authoritie I preached, is now at the <hi>requeſt</hi> of many <hi>religious</hi> friends prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and beggeth ſhelter and <hi>protection</hi> vnder your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips <hi>iudicious</hi> and reuerend <hi>approbation.</hi> It was <hi>harkened</hi> to attentiuely by the Honourable <hi>Lord MAYOR,</hi> and the publiſhing of it afterwards earneſtly requeſted by <hi>him,</hi> whoſe <hi>true loue</hi> to learning, may challenge a greater <hi>duety</hi> from more worthy <hi>hands,</hi> then theſe rude <hi>firſt-fruits</hi> of my paines at the <hi>Croſſe.</hi> Beſides, my <hi>excuſes</hi> may be, the <hi>raritie</hi> of Sermons in
<pb facs="tcp:12287:3"/>this <hi>Argument</hi> which is ſo neceſſary, the <hi>manifeſting</hi> of my deſire of <hi>doing</hi> good to my vttermoſt poore pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in Gods <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>teſtifying</hi> to the world that I deſire to giue ſome <hi>teſtimony</hi> of my vnfained thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to your Honour, who <hi>countenanced</hi> mee in the Vniuerſitie, where you were a zealous, religious, and worthy Gouernour. <hi>Sinne</hi> is more powerfull, now, in the <hi>dottage</hi> of the world, then it was in the <hi>nonage,</hi> ſo that there is neede of Pulpit and Preſse, to <hi>repreſſe</hi> it. I know your <hi>loue</hi> to the truth, which hath <hi>encouraged</hi> many, and now is ſo neceſſary to be <hi>manifeſted,</hi> the loue of many <hi>growing cold.</hi> My weekely labour, in that <hi>Paſtorall charge,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth much <hi>paynes,</hi> conſtrained me to take vp thoſe plaine notes, which I deliuered, and now haue retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>them,</hi> with an <hi>acknowledgement</hi> of the <hi>Authors</hi> names, which is the beſt reward that can be giuen to them in the iudgement of <hi>Patritius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Patrit.</hi> ep. l. de inſtit. resp. <hi>Baſ.</hi> p. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>Gr. Ier.</hi> apol. adu. <hi>Ruff. Gr.</hi> de <hi>Baſil.</hi>
               </note> and the aduiſe of <hi>Baſil</hi> to <hi>Gregory:</hi> Whoſe names concealed may brand a man with the note of <hi>theeuery,</hi> as <hi>Ierome</hi> ſpeaketh. God hath made your Honour <hi>a Kingly Pallace</hi> of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and placed you, in the eye of this <hi>Land,</hi> ouer this <hi>Honourable Citty:</hi> goe on in <hi>defending</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; ſo the Lord ſhall continue his graces to your <hi>Honour</hi> in this life, and multiply them with greater <hi>glory</hi> in a better <hi>life;</hi> for which I ſhall pray while I <hi>liue,</hi> and <hi>reſt</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Honors <hi>in all dutie to be commanded, SAMPSON PRICE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12287:3"/>
            <head>LONDONS WARNING BY <hi>Laodicea's</hi> Luke-warmneſſe.</head>
            <head type="sub">Lord Ieſus begin and end.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. 3.15.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I know thy workes, that thou art neyther colde nor hot, I would thou wert cold or hot. So then, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art luke-warme, and neyther colde nor hot, I will ſpue thee out of my mouth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 21.7.</note> the beſt beloued of the Diſciples, had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his cauſe before <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> that cruell Emperour, at <hi>Rome,</hi> and miraculouſly eſcaped out of the Caldron of <hi>boyling Oyle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doroth. vit. Pat.</note> he was bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed into the Ile of <hi>Pathmos;</hi> whence, he wrote this <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> where vſing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny zealous <hi>Prayers,</hi> and pouring forth bitter <hi>teares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. concio. de Baſil.</note>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:12287:4"/>which are the beſt weapons of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued much gracious content from aboue, and the <hi>Earth</hi> refuſing him, <note place="margin">Rupertus.</note> 
               <hi>Heauen</hi> embraced him. That as <hi>Dauid</hi> flying from <hi>Saul</hi> found a Kingdome, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.20. <hi>Elias</hi> from <hi>Iezabel</hi> an Angell to feed him, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.5. <hi>Paul</hi> from the <hi>Damaſcens,</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>Brethren</hi> to comfort him, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.27. So this bleſſed <hi>Exile</hi> had much <hi>glory</hi> in his greateſt <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi> For that God who ſhewed his viſions to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in the <hi>Mount, Gen.</hi> 22.12. to <hi>Iaacob</hi> in the <hi>field, Gen.</hi> 28. to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the <hi>ſtocks, Gen.</hi> 40. to <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Midian, Ex.</hi> 3. to <hi>Ieremy</hi> in the <hi>Priſon, Ier.</hi> 38. to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> in <hi>Babylon, Dan.</hi> 2. and to the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in the houſe of a <hi>Tanner, Act.</hi> 10. reuealeth to this our <hi>Euangeliſt, Apoſtle, Prophet,</hi> rapt vp in the Spirit, ſtrange things, which were to be <hi>done.</hi> The <hi>will of God</hi> being reuealed, it muſt be opened to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Richard.</hi> de ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto <hi>Victore</hi> 2. prol.</note> which were, like <hi>Dauids</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyes, more excellent then all others, 1 <hi>Ch:</hi> 12.14 and of which <hi>Iohn</hi> had the gouernment after <hi>Paul:</hi> but now, <hi>ſome</hi> had loſt their firſt loue; <hi>ſome</hi> were not faithfull to the death; <hi>ſome</hi> maintained the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Balaam</hi> and the <hi>Nicholaitans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Victorinus</hi> Epiſ. <hi>Clem. Al.</hi> Strom. <hi>Euſ.</hi> l. 3. c. 19. <hi>Irem.</hi> l. 1. c. 27.</note> that it was lawfull to eate of meate ſacrificed to <hi>Idols,</hi> that <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> was no ſinne: they ſuffered <hi>Iezabel</hi> to preach <hi>openly,</hi> and ſeduce <hi>many;</hi> they had but a <hi>name</hi> to liue, when they were <hi>dead:</hi> many of them were neyther <hi>cold</hi> nor <hi>hot,</hi> but proued <hi>falling Stars.</hi> This is the accuſation of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> and therefore it is reprehended by <hi>Iohn,</hi> and threatned by <hi>Christ,</hi> ſeruing, as a <hi>warning</hi> to all other <hi>Churches,</hi> leaſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12287:4"/>they be depriued of the Candleſticke of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Haymo. Paunonius.</note> 
               <hi>Which iudgement the Lord keepe from vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I know thy workes.</hi>] This whole <hi>Booke</hi> hath beene much regarded of the <hi>Ancients:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> ad <hi>Paulin. Euſ.</hi> l. 7. c. 23.</note> S. <hi>Ierome</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that it had as many <hi>myſteries</hi> as <hi>words. Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius Alexandrinus,</hi> confeſſed hee vnderſtood it not, and therefore did ſo much the more <hi>reuerence</hi> it by faith. <hi>Gilbertus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>H.</hi> card. <hi>Primaſ.</hi> praef. comm. <hi>Rupert.</hi> comm.</note> calleth it the excellenteſt of all <hi>Prophecies. Primaſius,</hi> thought it could neuer be prayſed enough. <hi>Rupertus,</hi> compared it to the Land of <hi>Promiſe,</hi> which the proud <hi>ſlandred,</hi> but the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>prayſed. Arias Montanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ar. Mo. <hi>praef.</hi>
               </note> after 30. yeeres ſtudy of it, ſaid it was <hi>obſcure</hi> vnto him, had hee not beene extraordinarily <hi>illuminated:</hi> but now the Booke is <hi>vnſealed,</hi> as you may read, <hi>c.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 10. It is not here as in the <hi>quadrature</hi> of a <hi>circle</hi> which may be <hi>knowne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quadratura cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi ſcibilis eſt at non datur ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> but the <hi>way</hi> is not yet <hi>found out:</hi> for the time is at <hi>hand</hi> when all things fore-told here, ſhall be <hi>fulfilled;</hi> this being a <hi>perfect Eccleſiaſticall ſtory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Strigelius.</note> from S. <hi>Iohn</hi> to the end of the <hi>world,</hi> of all materiall things in the <hi>Church.</hi> His <hi>Phraſe</hi> is <hi>Propheticall,</hi> his <hi>Method Logicall.</hi> He was <hi>Legatus à latere</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> one of his <hi>generall Ambaſſadours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 13.23. <hi>Dio. Carth.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>leaned on Ieſus</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. Hee had kept a long <hi>vacation</hi> in his ſolitary Pilgrimage, and ſeeing many dangers neare, hee forewarneth the <hi>Churches.</hi> The myſtery of <hi>iniquity</hi> began then to worke.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times, had her <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts,</hi> the tenne great <hi>Perſecutions</hi> beganne then to be rayſed vp; <hi>Hereſies</hi> after ſprouted forth; at laſt, by degrees the great <hi>Antichrist</hi> approached to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12287:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>his curſed ſeate, being to rule as a <hi>Monarch,</hi> and make warre againſt the Saints; which, when S. <hi>Iohn perceineth,</hi> he <hi>directed</hi> theſe <hi>familiar</hi> Epiſtles to encourage all <hi>ages</hi> to be <hi>zealous</hi> in the worke of <hi>the Lord,</hi> for he knoweth all their workes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I know.]</hi> Here are <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands, but <hi>Iaacobs</hi> voyce; hard ſpeeches, rough countenance, a ſtrong tempeſt of words, but an hidden ſpirit of <hi>tendernes</hi> and louing <hi>kindneſſe,</hi> proceeding from a mercifull <hi>Sauiour,</hi> who knew that vnleſſe they were toucht to the <hi>quicke,</hi> till blood were drawne, they would not be <hi>moued.</hi> The <hi>Paſtor</hi> was firſt to be blamed, whoſe name, whether it were <hi>Sagares,</hi> as ſome collect from <hi>Euſebius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 5. cap. 24.</note> or otherwiſe, I ſearch not. He gaue a bad <hi>preſident:</hi> for, <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.9.</note> like <hi>Prieſt,</hi> like <hi>people.</hi> The hearers grew <hi>cold,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſeeing, grieueth, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a meſſage; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in apo. hom. 2.</note> nay, commeth <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and knocketh, and ſpeaketh to all, ſpeaking to their Angell. <hi>O magna multitude dulcedinis Dei,</hi> as <hi>Caſsianus</hi> cryeth out: <note place="margin">Caſſ.</note> O the great multitude of the <hi>ſweet mercies</hi> of God, who keepeth <hi>the iuſt</hi> in him mouth, and neuer caſteth out ſinners before he admoniſh them, as here <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I know.]</hi> Wherein, let no man wonder that I the <hi>meaneſt</hi> and <hi>vnworthieſt</hi> of Gods <hi>meſſengers,</hi> haue choſen ſo <hi>thundring a Text:</hi> for beloued, <hi>ſilence</hi> can not breake the <hi>dead ſleepe of ſinne;</hi> ſoftneſſe of <hi>voyce</hi> can not pierce the heauy <hi>eares</hi> of this dull age; ordinary ſpeaking hath no proportion with extraordinary tranſgreſsion. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> muſt be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne with <hi>Trumpets</hi> and a <hi>ſhout:</hi> the Prophets
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12287:5"/>haue need of the zeale of <hi>Phinees,</hi> the gentle ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Eli</hi> is not ſufficient.</p>
            <p>VVhen I looke into the <hi>faſhions</hi> of the world, I ſee one maketh his <hi>Heauen</hi> of the <hi>droſſe</hi> and <hi>rubbiſh</hi> of the Earth: another maketh his <hi>belly</hi> his God: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Toad-like</hi> ſwelleth with <hi>ambition:</hi> another <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſus</hi>-like is enamored on <hi>natures dowry,</hi> his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; or <hi>natures</hi> ſhame, his <hi>apparell.</hi> The moſt, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> glory in their <hi>obſtinacy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 1.20. 2 Sam. 16.23. Act. 24.3. Dan. 4.7. 3 King. 18. 1 Sam 17.5. 1 King. 12.8. Ioh 7.48. Ioſh. 9.3.</note> or like <hi>Achitophel,</hi> in their <hi>pollicie,</hi> or like <hi>Tertullus,</hi> in their <hi>cloquence;</hi> or like <hi>Nabuchad-nezzar</hi> in their <hi>building;</hi> or like <hi>Zenacherib</hi> in their <hi>greatneſſe;</hi> or like <hi>Goliah</hi> in their <hi>ſtrength;</hi> or like <hi>Rehoboam</hi> in their <hi>birth;</hi> or like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in their <hi>knowledge;</hi> or like the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites</hi> in their <hi>craft.</hi> All <hi>theſe,</hi> and many <hi>other,</hi> are but bitter <hi>ſweets,</hi> gliding <hi>ſhaddowes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier 9.3.</note> gaudy <hi>toyes:</hi> yea, <hi>dung,</hi> in reſpect of good <hi>things:</hi> for which many <hi>hazard bodyes</hi> and <hi>ſoules,</hi> but they haue no courage <hi>for the trueth.</hi> All theſe may be rouzed vp by this threatning to <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which neglected <hi>Religion,</hi> and followed other <hi>things;</hi> and this is the <hi>ayme of my Text,</hi> being a taxe of the <hi>whole world,</hi> which is ſet on <hi>miſchiefe,</hi> toward the end, eſpecially of thoſe whoſe life is a <hi>Corban</hi> of vniuſt guiles and wicked gains, an <hi>Acheldama</hi> of blood &amp; oppreſſion, caring not who <hi>want,</hi> ſo they may abound: as alſo, of all thoſe who are like <hi>Salamanders,</hi> neuer <hi>liuing</hi> well but when they are in the fire of <hi>contention:</hi> who like <hi>Shemei</hi> while they ſeeke their ſeruant, <hi>riches,</hi> &amp; ſerue <hi>Mammon,</hi> looſe their beſt maſter, <hi>God:</hi> who haue good <hi>tongues,</hi> but the vſe them to <hi>deceit;</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12287:6"/>good <hi>wits,</hi> they vſe them to <hi>defend</hi> errours; ſtrong <hi>armes</hi> to murther; authoritie to <hi>oppreſſe,</hi> &amp; a good <hi>profeſsion</hi> to <hi>diſſemble.</hi> Theſe are the works of <hi>darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> which the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>light</hi> knoweth. Thus the <hi>forehead</hi> of ſinne hath loſt the <hi>bluſh</hi> of <hi>ſhame;</hi> the ſcore reacheth from the <hi>Eaſt</hi> to the <hi>Weſt,</hi> the cry of our <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> hath pierced the <hi>Clouds,</hi> the height of <hi>iniquitie</hi> is come to the top, and the fruits thereof are <hi>ripe:</hi> a dead <hi>coldneſſe</hi> hath ſtriken the <hi>hearts</hi> of many, hauing left them nothing but the <hi>bodies</hi> of men and <hi>viſors</hi> of Chriſtians: Neuer was the <hi>Iudge</hi> of all the Earth neerer to come, yet neuer was there ſo little <hi>preparation</hi> for his comming. Neuer was there more <hi>plenty</hi> of the Goſpel amongſt vs, yet neuer were men more <hi>vnthankefull</hi> &amp; <hi>fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi> then many of vs. In regard whereof, I haue thought this the fitteſt portion of <hi>Scripture</hi> that I could propoſe to you all. <hi>I know, &amp;c.</hi> As if brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus Chriſt had ſaid <hi>[I know thy workes:] Non approbando, ſed reprobando:</hi> not to <hi>allow</hi> them, but to reproue thee for them, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gloſe.</hi> Hugo Card.</note> as <hi>Hugo Card.</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. Eyther they were not in the way of the <hi>Lord</hi> (ſayth <hi>Meyerus</hi>) or they thought too well of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues already, or they <hi>feared</hi> to defend the <hi>truth</hi> publikely.</p>
            <p>[<hi>Thou art neither</hi> cold <hi>nor</hi> hot.] Neither an open <hi>enemie,</hi> nor truly zealous of the Goſpell, but a Gibeonite, an Ephraimit, a Canaanit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I would thou wert cold or hot.]</hi> Which he wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not ſimply that they were enemies vnto him, but in reſpect of that ſtate of luke-warmneſſe, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12287:6"/>which they were, <hi>becauſe</hi> ſooner they would come to <hi>Chriſt</hi> if they truſted not in themſelues. I would thou hadſt eyther the heat of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or the cold of <hi>Pagans,</hi> as <hi>Saluianus</hi> interpreteth it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[So then becauſe thou art luke-warme, &amp;c.]</hi> That is, ſeeing thou haſt neither the zeale of <hi>charitie</hi> to God, neither the acknowledgement of thine offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that by the feare of hell and repentance thou mighſt be drawne to <hi>good works,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> vpon the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I will ſpew thee out.]</hi> It is an <hi>alluſion</hi> to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>luke-warme</hi> water, which being <hi>drunke,</hi> eaſily <hi>procureth vomit;</hi> ſo our ſins (ſaith <hi>Aretius</hi>) cauſe Chriſt to caſt vs away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I know.]</hi> The ſumme of which <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> is, that the wicked <hi>Hypocrites</hi> ſhal be excommunicate from the true <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as <hi>Auguſt de Ancona</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, or as <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> Here we ſee, that the <hi>Lord</hi> tempereth all his rebukes with compaſſion, or as <hi>Conradus Graſerus:</hi> this is one of the beginnings of the <hi>infections of Antichriſtianiſme.</hi> You may call it <hi>the Worlds warning,</hi> or <hi>Englands drowſineſſe awaked,</hi> or rather LONDONS WARNING BY LAO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DICEAS LVKE-VVARMNES. Conſiſting of two generall parts. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diuiſ. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A ſolemne <hi>reprehenſion. I know thy works, &amp;c.</hi> 
               </item>
               <item>2. A zealous <hi>commination. So then, becauſe thou art luke-warme.</hi> 
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Subd. </seg>
               </label> In the firſt, You haue firſt an open <hi>proteſtation, I know thy workes, that thou, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. An <hi>optatiue compariſon. I would thou wert cold or hot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12287:7"/>
In the ſecond, you haue 1. a <hi>reaſon</hi> full of <hi>indig. nation, So then becauſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A <hi>puniſhment</hi> of <hi>eternall reiection. I will ſpew thee out of my mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 1. you haue the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> manifeſted.</p>
            <p>In the 2. you haue the <hi>Neuter</hi> condemned.</p>
            <p>In the 3. you haue <hi>Hypocrito</hi> threatned.</p>
            <p>In the 4. you haue the <hi>ſinner</hi> baniſhed.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>all which,</hi> while I ſhall <hi>ſpeake haſtely,</hi> as a <hi>paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> and plainely according to my <hi>ſmall abilitie,</hi> and accuſtomed <hi>method;</hi> let not any <hi>thing</hi> bee taken <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterly,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> knoweth, commeth from a <hi>poore ſinner,</hi> that wiſheth the <hi>flouriſhing of this Honourable Citty,</hi> &amp; the <hi>continuance</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> in this whole <hi>Kingdome,</hi> till <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> come to Iudgement. Let me deſire your <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> come to Iudgement. Let me deſire your <hi>Chriſtian, charitable,</hi> &amp; <hi>reuerend attention.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 11.9. Act. 2.15. Luke 22.53.</note> There are but 12. houres in the day, I ſhall keepe you <hi>only</hi> 2. of them: this is but little after the third <hi>houre</hi> of the <hi>day:</hi> let no man ſeeme ſo drouſie as if his <hi>heart</hi> were oppreſſed with <hi>ſurfetting, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe,</hi> or <hi>the cares of the world.</hi> It is your <hi>houre,</hi> and the Lord keepe vs all from the houre &amp; power of <hi>darkeneſſe,</hi> that wee may <hi>heare,</hi> and <hi>learne,</hi> and <hi>practiſe,</hi> the good <hi>leſſons</hi> ariſing from my <hi>Text.</hi> And ſo I come to the parts of <hi>my Text</hi> as they lye in order: and firſt, of my <hi>firſt circumſtance</hi> propoſed to be <hi>handled,</hi> wherein there is an <hi>open proteſtation, I know thy workes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>If we looke into the ſtate of <hi>Leoditea,</hi> wee ſhall finde, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plini.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5 c. 29. <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> in Epit. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll.</hi> in Apoc.</note> that it was the chiefeſt Citty of <hi>Aſia,</hi> built by <hi>Antiochus Theos,</hi> who put vpon it the name of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12287:7"/>wife. It was one of the moſt flouriſhing places of all <hi>Aſia minor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Camerarus</hi> in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. <hi>Strab.</hi> l. 12.</note> Here S. <hi>Paul preached,</hi> thinke hence he wrote his firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Timothy.</hi> It was the name alſo of a <hi>place</hi> in <hi>Phrygia;</hi> it had many worthy <hi>Miniſters</hi> after the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſ.</hi> l. 4. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. &amp; l. 7. c. 28.29.</note> as <hi>Socrates, Euſebius, Alexandrinus, Anatolius, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus, Theodorus</hi> and others. Here the <hi>great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> was decided about keeping the Paſſeouer. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melito</hi> l. de paſc.</note> It was waſhed through with the Riuer <hi>Licus.</hi> It had many honourable Citizens, as the rich <hi>Hiero, Zeno</hi> the Orator, and <hi>Polemo</hi> his <hi>ſonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gaſparus</hi> a Mel. <hi>Suarez.</hi> in text.</note> afterward made a king by <hi>Auguſtus.</hi> Their name is interpreted, <hi>A iuſt people,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but this auailed them nothing; for euill <hi>perſons</hi> may haue good names,<note place="margin">Lambert. Auen.</note> as <hi>Adoni-zedek</hi> the King of <hi>Ieruſlem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. 10.1.</note> who was an <hi>Idolater</hi> and a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> had a name ſignifying the <hi>Lord of Iuſtice,</hi> or the Iuſtice of the Lord. And one who was a grieuous perſecuter of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſ.</hi> Ecc. Hiſt. 9.9. 1 Kin. 12.32.</note> was tearmed <hi>Theot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onus,</hi> the <hi>childe of God. Bethel</hi> in <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams</hi> time, was vnwilling to part with the name of <hi>the houſe of God,</hi> but it rather deſerued to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Bethauen, the houſe of vanitie:</hi> ſo <hi>Laodicae</hi> abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her name, and the bleſſings of the Lord which were many, this aggrauateth the <hi>offence:</hi> for as the ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> was ſo much the more abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable being committed in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry of the <hi>foure and twenty men</hi> worſhipping the Sunne at the <hi>dore</hi> of the Temple of the <hi>Lord:</hi> ſo ſinne was <hi>more</hi> remarkable in theſe, of whom the Lord had <hi>deſsrued ſo well,</hi> and therefore hee now <hi>openeth</hi> them. <hi>I know, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12287:8"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Whence this <hi>Doctrine</hi> may be collected. </p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>knoweth the workes of all men, and will reueale them, be they neuer ſo cloſely hidden for a while.</hi> A <hi>proofe</hi> of this yee haue in the <hi>Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> who when hee had committed <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Murther,</hi> ſwallowed them for the greater part of a <hi>yeere,</hi> without any <hi>great remorſe.</hi> But <hi>Nathan</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to him, telleth him, thus ſaith the <hi>Lord; Thou diddeſt it ſecretly, as if none had ſeene it:</hi> I ſaw it, and will bring an open puniſhment vpon <hi>thee</hi> out of thine owne <hi>houſe</hi> before all Iſrael, and before the <hi>Sunne,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 12.11. This made <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne giue this aduiſe, <hi>In all thy wayes acknowledge him, and hee ſhall direct thy paths, Pro.</hi> 3.6. This was a <hi>charge</hi> giuen to <hi>Abraham</hi> when he was 99. yeers old, <hi>Walke before mee, and be perfect, Gen.</hi> 17.1. And it was the <hi>Oath of Elijah</hi> the <hi>Tiſhbite: As the Lord God of Iſrael liueth before whom</hi> I ſtand; 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.1.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Ieremy</hi> remembred the <hi>Iewes</hi> of, <hi>If thou returne, then will I bring thee againe, and thou ſhalt ſtand</hi> before mee, <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.19. All <hi>which,</hi> and many more, teach vs, that GOD <hi>ſeeth</hi> and <hi>knoweth</hi> our wayes be they neuer ſo ſecret. And no maruell; for if we climbe vp to <hi>Heauen</hi> hee is there, if wee goe downe to the <hi>center</hi> of the earth, he is there alſo: he is euery where and no where; euery where, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhing the <hi>place</hi> with his <hi>beeing</hi> and <hi>power;</hi> no where; by <hi>circumſcription</hi> and locall <hi>definition.</hi> Hee is within all things, not <hi>included;</hi> without all things, not <hi>excluded;</hi> below all things, not <hi>degraded;</hi> aboue all things, not <hi>preferred:</hi> therefore he proclaimeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12287:8"/>to LAODICEA, that hee <hi>knoweth her workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 2. v. 1.</note> hee holdeth the 7. <hi>Starres</hi> in his right hand, and walketh in the midſt of the 7. <hi>golden Candleſtickes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> hee is firſt and laſt, was dead, <note place="margin">v. 8.</note> and is aliue.</p>
            <p>In that to <hi>Pergamus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 12.</note> hee hath the ſharpe Sword with two edges.</p>
            <p>In that to <hi>Thiatyra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 18.</note> he hath eyes like a flame of fire, and feet like fine braſſe.</p>
            <p>In that to <hi>Sardis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 3. v. 1.</note> he hath the 7. Spirits of God.</p>
            <p>In that to <hi>Philadelphia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 7.</note> hee is called holy and true, hauing the key of <hi>Dauid,</hi> which openeth, and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth and no man openeth.</p>
            <p>And in this to <hi>Laodicea,</hi> hee is called <hi>Amen,</hi> the faithfull and true witnes, the beginning of the <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;</hi> and the <hi>knower of all workes</hi> in my <hi>Text.</hi> Hee <hi>commendeth</hi> ſome, and <hi>diſcommendeth</hi> others, <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> all. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Smyrna</hi> was a good man, though poore to the <hi>world, I know thy pouerty, but thou art</hi> rich. <hi>c.</hi> 2.9. Thou haſt done good ſeruice to the <hi>Church,</hi> and haſt little reward of <hi>man:</hi> Be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto the death, and I will giue thee the crowne of life. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> was a worthy man, not of the greateſt gifts, yet faithful in a little. <hi>Thou haſt a little ſtrength, and kept my word. c.</hi> 3.8. Chriſt promiſeth to bleſſe his labours, and make his enemies know that he is in the loue of God: but <hi>Epheſus</hi> is reproued for going back-ward. <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thiatyra,</hi> for maintayning corrupt doctrine. <hi>Sardis,</hi> for dulneſſe, deafeneſſe, and vnſoundneſſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12287:9"/>in the worſhipping of God: and <hi>Laodicea</hi> here for luke-warmeneſſe. The ground of his <hi>prayſes</hi> and <hi>diſpraiſes</hi> is, that he knoweth their workes, ſeauen times repeated, that is, all their particular <hi>actions;</hi> yea, their very <hi>thoughts,</hi> and therefore cannot be <hi>deceiued.</hi> Men may erre in their cenſures of others, becauſe they know not the <hi>hearts,</hi> and with what <hi>affections,</hi> cannot faile <hi>one iot,</hi> therefore he ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth their <hi>mouthes</hi> at the firſt, leaſt they ſhould <hi>reply</hi> any thing, <hi>I know thy</hi> workes. I know what thou <hi>art,</hi> and what thou <hi>haſt beene;</hi> I know thy <hi>ſitting downe,</hi> and thy <hi>riſing vp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>illimited</hi> knowledge of God is amplyfied by <hi>wonderfull</hi> teſtimonies throughout the <hi>Bible,</hi> I ſtay not your eares with commemoration of the places. There is neyther <hi>heuaen</hi> nor <hi>hell,</hi> nor the vttermoſt <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Sea,</hi> neyther <hi>day</hi> nor <hi>night, light</hi> nor <hi>darkeneſſe,</hi> that can hide vs from his face: the <hi>thoughts</hi> of our <hi>harts, words</hi> of our <hi>tongues, wayes</hi> of our <hi>feet;</hi> nay, our <hi>bones,</hi> our mothers <hi>wombes</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we <hi>lay</hi> in our firſt <hi>informitie</hi> and <hi>imperfection,</hi> are well knowne vnto him. He ſitteth vpon the <hi>Circle</hi> of heauen, and beholdeth the <hi>inhabitants</hi> of the earth as <hi>Graſhoppers:</hi> his Throne is the <hi>Heauen</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, the <hi>Earth</hi> is his <hi>foote-ſtoole;</hi> his wayes are in the <hi>great deepe.</hi> The <hi>ignorance</hi> of this, is the cauſe of all <hi>ſinne,</hi> of <hi>curſing, deceit, fraud, miſchiefe,</hi> and <hi>vanity,</hi> becauſe men haue not God in their <hi>thoughts. Pſal.</hi> 10.4.</p>
            <p>This made <hi>Nazian</hi> confeſſe that a man ought<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Naz.</hi> Orat. de Theolog.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12287:9"/>no <hi>oftner</hi> to breath then to remember CHRIST, and <hi>Ephreem</hi> to ſay, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> to. 2. c. 10.</note> that men conſidering the knowledge of GOD, will auoyd <hi>offences</hi> as <hi>male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors</hi> abroad will <hi>thefts,</hi> at the drawing neere of <hi>Aſsiſes.</hi> By this meanes hee recalled a foule <hi>ſoule</hi> that long had liued in <hi>abhomination:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Metaphraſtes in eius vita.</note> ſhee deſired <hi>Ephreem</hi> to lye with her, which hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, vnleſſe it were in the mids of <hi>the Citie,</hi> ſhee ſayde it would bee a publike ſhame to both: How much <hi>more</hi> ſayd hee, is it in the <hi>ſight of God</hi> and his <hi>Angels?</hi> which words ſo <hi>ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> her, that ſhee repented and became a <hi>faithfull</hi> conuert.</p>
            <p>It was the aduiſe of <hi>Seneca</hi> the Philoſopher, <note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> though an Heathen, to his friend <hi>Lucilius,</hi> that in all his <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>thoughts,</hi> hee ſhould ſo carry himſelfe, as if ſome good man ſaw him and would <hi>blame</hi> him if he erred; but wee muſt haue <hi>God</hi> alwayes before <hi>our eyes,</hi> and being at our right hand, wee ſhall not be <hi>moued,</hi> our heart ſhall bee <hi>glad,</hi> our glory ſhall <hi>reioyce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.9.</note> our <hi>fleſh</hi> alſo ſhall reſt in <hi>hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely, there is no <hi>way</hi> to hide our ſelues from him: <hi>diſguiſed</hi> ADAM in his <hi>Figge-leaued coat,</hi> cloſe amongſt the buſhes, could not ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter himſelfe from his knowledge, no more can wee. <hi>Videt omnia generaliter ſine exceptione, euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſine dubitatione, immutabiliter ſine obliuione.</hi> Hee ſeeth all things generally, <hi>without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> euidently <hi>without doubting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nich. Denijfi.</note> vnchangeably <hi>without forgetting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:12287:10"/>
He entereth the <hi>priuy</hi> chamber of the heart, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is <hi>impoſsible</hi> to blind his eyes, or to auoyd him by flying, <note place="margin">Viex inftit. ad poenit.</note> and therefore <hi>poore runne-away, Non te Domino abſcondis, ſed Dominum abſcondis tibi.</hi> Thou hideſt not thy ſelfe from God, but God from thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Vſe 1. Is to <hi>condemne</hi> the ignorant <hi>ſinners</hi> of this age, <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 27.19.</note> who ſinning ſecretly ſay, <hi>Who ſeeth vs? we are compaſſed about with darkneſſe, the wals couer vs, what need we feare? the</hi> moſt High <hi>will not remember our ſinnes; ſuch onely feare the eyes</hi> of men, <hi>and know not that the eyes of</hi> the Lord <hi>are</hi> tenne thouſand <hi>times brighter then the</hi> Sun, <hi>beholding all the wayes of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet thou <hi>blaſphemous Atheiſt,</hi> hearken to this, whenſoeuer (as I hope there is none in this <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Congregation</hi>) who runneſt on in thy ſinnes, <note place="margin">Heb. 4.13.</note> and thinkeſt that God knoweth them not; yes, he <hi>knoweth all things,</hi> all things <hi>are naked and open</hi> to the eyes of <hi>him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note> he ſearcheth <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and puniſheth the men that are ſetled on their lees. They know this, and remember ſometimes that for all things they muſt <hi>come to iudgement.</hi> This is the reaſon that the <hi>faces</hi> of ſuch are vſually <hi>pale and gaſtly:</hi> their <hi>ſmiles</hi> and <hi>laughters</hi> faint and hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: their <hi>ſpeeches</hi> doubtfull, and full of <hi>abrupt ſtops,</hi> and <hi>vnſeaſonable</hi> turnings: their <hi>purpoſes</hi> and <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> vnſteedy and ſauoring of much <hi>diſtraction.</hi> Hence are thoſe vaine <hi>changes</hi> of places, and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies</hi> like the ſicke patients, though <hi>remoued,</hi> yet complaine ſtill of vnabated <hi>torments:</hi> like the ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Deere hauing receiued a <hi>deadly arrow,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12287:10"/>ſhaft ſhaken out hath left the head <hi>behind</hi> it, running from one thicket to another, not able to change his paine with his place, but finding his <hi>wounds</hi> worſe with continuance: VVith <hi>Nero</hi> they may change their <hi>bed-chamber,</hi> but fiends will attend them. They may ſend their <hi>ſoule</hi> from their <hi>body,</hi> but neuer their <hi>conſcience</hi> from their <hi>ſoule,</hi> nor their <hi>ſinne</hi> from their <hi>conſcience.</hi> Neither prophane <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretius</hi> with his <hi>Epicurean</hi> rules of confidence: nor drunken <hi>Anacreon</hi> with his wanton <hi>odes,</hi> can ſhift of the violent <hi>horrour</hi> of this aduerſary. A medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation fit for the corruptions of <hi>theſe times,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may complaine as <hi>Tertullian</hi> did. <hi>O nos mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeros qui Chriſtiani dicimur hoc tempore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iewel</hi> in Apol.</note> 
               <hi>gentes agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ſub nomine Chriſti.</hi> O miſerable men that we are, many of vs are called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this name couer many ſinnes of the Gentiles. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> pag. 3. c. 7.</note> And as S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaid of the pittifull eſtate of his time, Wee that are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are hated of the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> for our vices ſake, wee are now become a <hi>wonder,</hi> not onely to <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> but euen to all the <hi>wicked and vngodly:</hi> or as more lately <hi>Gue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uara:</hi> The <hi>Philoſophers</hi> beleeued as <hi>Pagans,</hi> but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> wee beleeue like <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but liue like <hi>Pagans.</hi> How many amongſt vs <hi>wallow</hi> in immoderate <hi>pleaſures,</hi> hauing wanton <hi>eyes,</hi> ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>mouthes,</hi> painted <hi>faces,</hi> lickerous <hi>tongues,</hi> ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>hands,</hi> following no <hi>vocation,</hi> more <hi>ambitious</hi> of the title of good-fellowſhip then of <hi>Religion?</hi> Their <hi>ſenſes</hi> are their procurors, <hi>appetite</hi> their ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and <hi>luſt</hi> their Maſters: they are the liuing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12287:11"/>
               <hi>tombes</hi> of their Fore-fathers, and Poſterities. How many, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. de ciu. c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Qui magis erubeſcunt ſi villam malam habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, quam ſi vitam:</hi> who bluſh more hauing an ill ordered <hi>Farme,</hi> or <hi>houſe,</hi> then a wicked <hi>Life?</hi> How many who <hi>profeſſe</hi> that <hi>they know</hi> GOD, <hi>but in workes deny him, being abhominable, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient, and vnto euery good worke reprobate? Tit.</hi> 1.16. How many who loue in <hi>word</hi> and in <hi>tongue,</hi> but not <hi>in deede and in truth?</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.18. How many that cry <hi>Lord, Lord, yet neuer doe the will of the Lord which is in heauen? Mat.</hi> 7.21. The Lord <hi>knoweth</hi> the wayes and workes of theſe to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and they ſhall periſh, for their benummed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to doe any good. <hi>I know, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> A ſecond vſe of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> may be to teach vs, that ſeeing all our workes are <hi>manifeſt</hi> to him, wee worke out our <hi>Saluation</hi> with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. Wee haue beene long <hi>taught</hi> that wee are ſaued by <hi>Faith,</hi> without the works of the law, which though it be a moſt true poſition, and ſoundly <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> and flatly <hi>concluded Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 28. Yet being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood amiſſe it hath beene the cauſe of <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme,</hi> and the neglect of good deeds. It hath made many amongſt vs wiſh Chriſt to doe <hi>all,</hi> they will doe <hi>nothing</hi> for <hi>themſelues.</hi> It is a true <hi>challenge</hi> I confeſſe of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> for the <hi>all-ſufficiencie</hi> of Chriſt his merit. <hi>It is I, it is euen I which for mine owne ſake put away thine iniquities, Iſ.</hi> 43. Not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> nor <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor <hi>Peter,</hi> nor <hi>Paul.</hi> It is not the <hi>preparation</hi> of a mans owne <hi>nature,</hi> nor the <hi>liberty</hi> of his owne <hi>will,</hi> nor the <hi>cooperation</hi> of his owne <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:12287:11"/>for, <hi>eternall life is the gift of God, through Ieſus Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 6.23. But yet this gift is beſtowed onely vpon thoſe for whom it is <hi>prepared, Mat.</hi> 20.23. which haue exerciſed themſelues in the works of <hi>mercy, Mat.</hi> 25.35. not that theſe are the cauſes of <hi>ſaluation,</hi> and by them we ſhould <hi>merit,</hi> as the <hi>Rhemists</hi> affirme in their <hi>Annotations, Ro.</hi> 2 <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the <hi>Papiſts Pithagoras maintayneth, l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>De bonis operibus.</hi> The ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> are againſt it. <hi>Baſil. orat. de Humil. Quid te effers tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in bonis proprijs? Quid enim habes quod non accepiſti?</hi> Why doſt thou boaſt of any good works as though they were thine owne? what haſt thou, that thou haſt not receiued? So, <hi>Chriſ. in</hi> 2. <hi>co. ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 11. <hi>A gratia iuſtificatio fit, Deo totum praeſtante:</hi> Our Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is from God, hee worketh the whole. So, <hi>Ber. in can. ſe.</hi> 61. <hi>Meritum meum miſeratio Domini:</hi> My merit is the Lords mercy. So, <hi>Orig.</hi> on 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> It lyeth vpon vs to <hi>ſearch</hi> who was iuſtified by faith without <hi>works,</hi> and for example, (ſaith he) I thinke vpon the <hi>Theefe,</hi> who being crucified with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> cryed vnto him; <hi>Lord remember me when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into thy Kingdome:</hi> and there is no other good <hi>worke</hi> of his mentioned in the Goſpell, but for this <hi>alone</hi> faith, Ieſus ſaith vnto him, <hi>This night thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I <hi>ſpeake</hi> not this to with-draw men from doing good, or to diſcourage them in their <hi>charitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions.</hi> Wee allow <hi>good workes,</hi> and preach them to our <hi>hearers;</hi> yea, ſome of our Church publiſh whole <hi>Treatiſes,</hi> that good workes are <hi>neceſſary to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12287:12"/>ſaluation.</hi> Let this therefore be a witneſſe againſt our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> the Papiſts, who ſlander vs, ſaying, that wee teach onely <hi>negatiue</hi> doctrines, and not <hi>affirmatiue</hi> Poſitions. For we <hi>proclaime</hi> to the world that <hi>Faith</hi> is dead if it haue no <hi>workes:</hi> wee vrge <hi>Gods Commandements,</hi> which we are to obey; his <hi>Honour</hi> which wee are to ſeeke; <hi>Chriſts example,</hi> which wee are to follow; the <hi>Vocation</hi> of Chriſtians, which requireth a life anſwerable to our profeſſion; the <hi>Reward</hi> promiſed to thoſe that keepe Gods Lawes; the <hi>ſcandall</hi> that enſueth of lewd actions; the <hi>Curſe</hi> that is denounced againſt the tranſgreſſors.</p>
            <p>Wee haue a great <hi>aduantage</hi> of them for good workes.</p>
            <p>We <hi>propoſe</hi> to our ſelues the example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; they <hi>follow</hi> Antichriſt, and the founders of diuers Orders of Monkes, and Fryars, and Nuns, who were rather <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> then <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, ceremonious</hi> then holy and <hi>religious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We <hi>force</hi> none to forſweare Marriage; they <hi>ſuffer</hi> none of their Clergy to marry, whereof many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations <hi>follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We <hi>count</hi> it a thing horrid for men profeſſing Chriſtianitie, to <hi>empoyſon</hi> and <hi>murther</hi> thoſe that are oppoſite to them in Religion; they <hi>count</hi> ſuch meritorious, and honour the Aſſaſſiners as Saints.</p>
            <p>Wee <hi>allow</hi> no <hi>Indulgences</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> but they are <hi>confident</hi> vpon them.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe wee liue in the <hi>dottage</hi> of the world, wherein the harts of many are hardned from <hi>doing good:</hi> yet howſoeuer in the time of King EDVVARD
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12287:12"/>the firſt the Statute of <hi>Mortmaine</hi> was enacted, whereby it was <hi>prouided,</hi> that none ſhould giue any thing to the Church without the eſpeciall licenſe of the King, which is yet vnrepealed, yet in this <hi>laſt age,</hi> and in the <hi>remembrance</hi> of ſome yet <hi>liuing:</hi> ſince the cleare <hi>Sunne-ſhine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened the <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> there haue beene more <hi>Colledges</hi> founded, more <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, more <hi>Libraries</hi> and <hi>Schooles</hi> builded, more <hi>poore Schollers</hi> maintained, more <hi>Orphans</hi> and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent</hi> relieued, more <hi>charitable deedes</hi> exerciſed generally in our Land, particularly in this <hi>famous</hi> Citie, euer renowmed for her good workes, then in many ages vnder <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know there are ſome <hi>in,</hi> but not <hi>of,</hi> our <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe chiefe <hi>ſtudy,</hi> is to rob GOD and the <hi>Leuite</hi> of the little portion of <hi>Tithes</hi> and <hi>Offerings,</hi> which cannot be <hi>denyed</hi> to be due <hi>iure diuino.</hi>
               <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Carleton.</hi>
               </note> Wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>ſay</hi> of ſuch as the <hi>Iew</hi> did of the <hi>Centurion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 7.5.</note> 
               <hi>Hee loueth our Nation, and hath built vs a Sinagogue,</hi> or as the Prophet DAVID did of himſelfe; they deſire to behold the <hi>beauty</hi> of the Temple of the <hi>Lord,</hi> but their cry is, <hi>let vs take the houſes, and barnes, &amp; lands of the Church in poſſeſsion,</hi> and for the honour of the <hi>Prieſt-hood: Downe with it, downe with it, euen to the ground,</hi> but that <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> ſhall holde, <hi>Quae malignè contraxit Pater,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet. Ble.</hi> ep. 10.</note> 
               <hi>luxu peiori refundet Haeres;</hi> That which the Father hath wickedly ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped together, the ſonne ſhall <hi>more</hi> wickedly ſcatter abroad. It is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of the ruine of ſo many great <hi>Families</hi> in this kingdome. Let him that hath an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12287:13"/>eare hearken to this; when you <hi>craue,</hi> begge not that <hi>which is Gods;</hi> when you <hi>giue,</hi> giue not that <hi>which is Gods;</hi> when you <hi>buy,</hi> buy not that <hi>which is Gods;</hi> when yee ſell, ſell not that <hi>which is Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here let me giue our <hi>religious</hi> King IAMES that <hi>teſtimony</hi> which <hi>Petrus Bleſenſis</hi> left to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond; <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Benedictus Dominus, qui Regem</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum <hi>atalibus hactenus conſeruauit innoxium;</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be that GOD which hitherto hath <hi>defended</hi> his <hi>Maieſty</hi> from all kinde of Sacriledge, that hath not <hi>furniſhed</hi> his <hi>houſe</hi> with the <hi>ſpoyle</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> nor <hi>increaſed</hi> his <hi>Reuenue</hi> by the <hi>loſſe</hi> of Gods <hi>houſe,</hi> nor <hi>defiled</hi> his hands with <hi>Symonie,</hi> nor <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed</hi> his <hi>Preferments</hi> for perſonall <hi>fauour</hi> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And beſides his <hi>Maieſties</hi> care, many <hi>Ebed-me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech's</hi> there are in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 38.9.</note> ſpeaking for the Prophets of the Lord, that they may haue main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</p>
            <p>Many <hi>Obadiahs</hi> ready to hide the Seruants of GOD from dangers.</p>
            <p>Many <hi>liberall Benefactors</hi> giuing voluntary <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, depoſita pietatis;</hi> Pledges and teſtimonies of their <hi>Pietie</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tert.</hi> Apologet.</note> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calleth them, <hi>Sacrifices</hi> as acceptable to GOD as that of ABEL, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gr. Naz</hi> c. 1. contra <hi>Iulia.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Naz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many good <hi>Shunamites</hi> perſwading their <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands</hi> to make a <hi>Chamber,</hi>
               <note place="margin">s Kings 4.10.</note> to ſet forth a <hi>Bed,</hi> and a <hi>Table,</hi> and a <hi>Stoole,</hi> and a <hi>Candle</hi> for the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of God, <hi>when they come to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many</hi> with <hi>Zachaus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19.6.</note> who ioyfully <hi>receiue</hi> into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12287:13"/>their houſes them that bring the <hi>glad tidings of</hi> ſaluation. <note place="margin">Luk. 19.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And in this <hi>luke-warme</hi> age ſome there are who are <hi>holy,</hi> and humble men of heart, reſolute <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> who like <hi>him</hi> in the Poet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucem &amp; aethera petit &amp; teſte ſole viuit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. Tr. Hip.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walking</hi> in <hi>ſinceritie</hi> as it were in view of the <hi>Sun; walking</hi> in the <hi>light</hi> as children of the <hi>light;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ge. 25.27. Ioh. 1.47.</note> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the ſteps of vertuous <hi>Iacob,</hi> who was a plaine man; and of <hi>Nathaniel</hi> a true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeede, in whom was no guile. Though it cannot be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but that there are more, neither <hi>hot</hi> nor <hi>cold,</hi> whom becauſe I ſhall deale with in my ſecond <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall part,</hi> I proceed to my next <hi>circumſtance</hi> of the firſt generall, where you haue the optatiue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I would, &amp;c.] The</hi> Church <hi>of God reioyſing in her</hi> husband, <note place="margin">Iae. 2<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt; ſaith that he was like a</hi> Roe <hi>or a young</hi> Hart, <hi>leaping vpon the</hi> Mountaines, <hi>and skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vpon the</hi> Hils. <hi>Can.</hi> 2.8.9. <hi>Propter acerrimum viſum &amp; velocem curſum ad omnes fines terrae,</hi> as <hi>Philo</hi> interpreteth it. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philo.</hi> carpat. Epiſc.</note> It is in regard of his quicke <hi>ſight</hi> and ſwift <hi>courſe</hi> into all the parts of the <hi>world.</hi> His meaſures vvere from heauen to the <hi>wombe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyra.</note> from the <hi>wombe</hi> to the <hi>cratch,</hi> from the <hi>cratch</hi> to the <hi>croſſe,</hi> from the <hi>croſſe</hi> to the <hi>graue,</hi> from the <hi>graue</hi> to <hi>heauen;</hi> behould hee commeth, his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe quickly, and ſtill is in trauell to his <hi>Church</hi> with <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>wiſhes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I would, &amp;c.]</hi> The <hi>driuing</hi> of his <hi>Chariot</hi> is like the <hi>driuing of Iehu,</hi> hee ſpeaketh in <hi>haſt,</hi> the time
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12287:14"/>with him, is as the time of <hi>loue.</hi> His <hi>loue</hi> is as ſtrong as <hi>death,</hi> the <hi>flames</hi> of it are Diuine <hi>flames,</hi> neuer <hi>dying,</hi> the coles thereof as the coles of <hi>Iuniper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aske the <hi>dayes that</hi> are paſt ſince God created <hi>man</hi> vpon the earth, from the one end of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the other, if euer there were ſuch a <hi>thing</hi> as this. Did euer any <hi>heare</hi> the voyce of God ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>forme</hi> of a <hi>petitioner? O thou diuine and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall peace-maker, the ſauiour of men, the annointed of God, mediatour betwixt God and man, in whom there is nothing, which doth not exceed, not onely the conceite, but the very wonder of Angels, who ſaw thee in thy humiliation, with ſilence, and adore thee in thy glory, with perpetuall praiſes, we ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at thy loue, emptying thy ſelfe of glory, that thou mighteſt put on ſhame, and miſery, to be the ſinners oratour and ſacrifice.</hi> Hee ſayd not as <hi>Dauid,</hi> vvould God I <hi>had dyed for thee,</hi> O <hi>Abſolon,</hi> my <hi>ſonne:</hi> God knoweth, hee dyed for <hi>our ſinnes,</hi> the cauſe moſt <hi>odious:</hi> the <hi>iust</hi> for the <hi>vniust,</hi> the <hi>perſons</hi> vnequall: to bring vs to God, the <hi>end</hi> moſt <hi>abſolute:</hi> and ſtill hee applyeth this to his <hi>Church,</hi> ſpeaking by his <hi>Ministers,</hi> pleading for vs in <hi>heauen,</hi> perſwading vs on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I would.] Laodicea</hi> was in a <hi>conſumption,</hi> her <hi>hands</hi> were ſicke, her <hi>members</hi> weake, her <hi>Phiſitian</hi> &amp; Paſtour fearefull, her <hi>zeale</hi> was at the laſt <hi>gaſpe,</hi> her <hi>enemies</hi> were round about her, ready to <hi>laugh</hi> at her <hi>deſtruction,</hi> for being neither <hi>cold nor hote:</hi> This maketh <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo earneſt. Hee is not <hi>like</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> which diſpenſeth with his <hi>followers</hi> to worſhip
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12287:14"/>God, with their <hi>lippes,</hi> and diſſemble their <hi>religion,</hi> and forſweare their <hi>opinion,</hi> and come to <hi>Sermons,</hi> and ſubſcribe to our <hi>lawes,</hi> and ſeeme <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> as the <hi>diuell</hi> licenceth <hi>witches</hi> to ſeeme <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo they giue him their heart, as <hi>appeared</hi> by many in the beginning of <hi>Queene</hi> ELIZABETHS raigne, hauing <hi>an agnus Dei,</hi> with <hi>Da mihi cor:</hi> hee cannot endure a <hi>Neuter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[I would.]</hi> For there are but two <hi>wayes, vna fidei in caliditate charitatis,</hi> one of <hi>faith</hi> in the heate of charitie, leading to life <hi>euerlaſting,</hi> another of <hi>cold diſtruſt</hi> in Chriſt, drawing to <hi>destruction.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nardus</hi> in text.</note> But I come to the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which is this properly.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Doct. <hi>It is better to be an open ſinner then a doubtfull Neuter.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bar.</hi> apol. ad <hi>Guli. Abb.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Barnard</hi> I confeſſe made a <hi>queſtion</hi> of it. <hi>Quis horum magis impius?</hi> Who is the more wicked, whether hee, that openly profeſſeth <hi>impietie,</hi> or hee that <hi>falſely</hi> counterfeiteth <hi>ſanctitie?</hi> But here the queſtion is <hi>anſwered,</hi> and the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie <hi>decided</hi> by Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Looke vpon the <hi>Iew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gr.</hi> 3. p. paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral admon. 35.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> he ſeemeth to beleeue, but is incredulous: the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile</hi> is more tollerable; which can ſay, <hi>I neuer knew the Law, I neuer heard the Prophets:</hi> neyther can be <hi>excuſed;</hi> yet hee <hi>ſinneth</hi> leſſe, which doth not the <hi>workes</hi> which hee neuer <hi>knew</hi> were to be <hi>done,</hi> then hee that <hi>knew</hi> his <hi>Maiſters</hi> will, <hi>read</hi> it, and <hi>denyed</hi> it. It had beene better for ſuch, not to haue knowne the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> then after they haue knowne it, to <hi>turne</hi> from the holy <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> deliuered vnto them. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12287:15"/>This made CHRIST tell the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that <hi>Publicanes</hi> and <hi>Harlots</hi> ſhould goe before them, into the Kingdome of Heauen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.31. for they ſeeing their ſinnes, <hi>repented</hi> at the <hi>Preaching</hi> of <hi>Iohn.</hi> So hee tolde the <hi>Phariſees; If yee were blinde yee ſhould haue no ſinne, but now you ſay, We ſee: therefore your ſinne</hi> remayneth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.41. The open ſinner <hi>reuealeth</hi> himſelfe that wee may <hi>auoyd</hi> him, but the <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> walketh ſo ſecretly, that wee know not how to iudge him; therefore they are more odious then the other.</p>
            <p>In regard whereof, <hi>Licurgus</hi> baniſhed <hi>Neuters</hi> his Common-wealth. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aul. Gel.</hi> l. 2. c. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Solon</hi> prohibited them by his Law. <hi>Elias</hi> forbad that there ſhould be any amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to worſhip GOD and <hi>Baal. Moſes</hi> would not haue men to weare mixt gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets of <hi>Linnen</hi> and <hi>Wollen,</hi> and CHRIST pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth that no man can ſerue two <hi>Maiſters,</hi> GOD and <hi>Mammon,</hi> the <hi>true</hi> Church and the <hi>falſe, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi> The abuſes hee ſtriketh at, are <hi>doubling</hi> in the Worſhip of GOD, <hi>blending</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Falſhood:</hi> yet ſome, eyther in <hi>hope</hi> of gaine, or out of their <hi>rotten affections,</hi> or out of their <hi>Machiauillian Policie,</hi> would haue many Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions <hi>tollerated</hi> in one Kingdome: nay, as <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> compoſed a <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Indaiſme</hi> and <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie,</hi> ſo, many would reconcile the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and haue both liue together. But farre be this <hi>Realme of ours</hi> from ſuch <hi>corruption.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Let all good people ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>For, as <hi>Anthony</hi> ſometimes King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:12287:15"/>ſaid to the <hi>Ambaſſadour</hi> of the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Comment. Relig. &amp; reipub. in <hi>Gallia.</hi>
               </note> exhorting the reformed <hi>French</hi> to be of <hi>Luthers</hi> Doctrine; There be <hi>forty</hi> points, wherein <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin</hi> doe differ from the <hi>Pope,</hi> and in <hi>nine and thirty</hi> of them they agree betweene <hi>themſelues,</hi> and in that ſingle <hi>one</hi> they diſſent: ſo wee <hi>pray</hi> vnto the Lord for the reconciling of thoſe vnto vs: but the <hi>differences</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are ſo <hi>many,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſc. <hi>Lond.</hi> in <hi>Ionam.</hi>
               </note> and ſo <hi>Diametrally</hi> oppoſed, as the Northern and Southern <hi>Poles</hi> ſhall ſooner meete together, then our opinions, <hi>ſtanding</hi> as they doe, bee <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled.</hi> Therefore neuer looke for a <hi>Reconciliation</hi> or <hi>Tolleration.</hi> One Heauen held not <hi>Michael</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> in peace; nor one Houſe, the <hi>Arke</hi> and <hi>Dagon;</hi> nor one Wombe, <hi>Iaacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau;</hi> nor one Temple, <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Marchandiſing;</hi> nor one Camp, the <hi>cleane</hi> and <hi>Leprous;</hi> nor one Bath, <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Cerinthus;</hi> nor one Tongue, GOD and <hi>Milchom;</hi> nor one Conſcience, <hi>our Religion</hi> and <hi>Popery.</hi> I would to GOD there were not many <hi>Laodiceans</hi> amongſt vs, that vrged this <hi>Caueat,</hi> who eyther afraid of <hi>danger,</hi> or pining with ſloath, ſit <hi>downe</hi> and are zealous neyther way.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> If they obiect for themſelues, wee loue to be <hi>quiet</hi> and not factious, <hi>Vertue</hi> followeth the <hi>meane,</hi> we will be <hi>ſtiffe</hi> for neyther <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I anſwere, if it were in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>indifferencie,</hi> if wee might goe on eyther ſide without <hi>danger,</hi> then <hi>Platoes</hi> aduiſe is good; ſo to deale in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as to hurt neyther <hi>Parents</hi> nor <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try:</hi> And that of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> ep. 86. ad <hi>Caſul.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In ijs rebus de
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12287:16"/>quibus nihil ſtatuit diuinae Scripturae certa praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, &amp;c.</hi> In thoſe things which the <hi>Scripture</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth not certainly, eyther the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of <hi>Gods people,</hi> or the <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> of our <hi>Anceſtours</hi> are to be held for <hi>Lawes.</hi> Wee muſt take heede, leaſt by the tempeſt of <hi>Contention</hi> the <hi>calmneſſe</hi> of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> be inueloped. And that of Saint <hi>Ambroſe, Si non vultis errare, &amp;c.</hi> If yee will not erre, doe as I; to what Church ſoeuer I come, I apply my ſelfe to the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of it: <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>ad</hi> Ian.</note> which if it had beene followed by ſome in this Church, the Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie would <hi>neuer</hi> haue inſulted ouer vs, for <hi>iarring in Diſcipline:</hi> but as good <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſ.</hi> l. 2. de vita <hi>Conſt.</hi> c. 67.</note> that great <hi>Emperour exhorted Arius</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> to put away a fooliſh <hi>Queſtion</hi> that fired the Church, ſo our gracious <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> like a bleſſed <hi>Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker,</hi> hath decided the difference of <hi>indifferent</hi> ceremonyes, and giuen the <hi>counſell</hi> of the other worthy Monarch. There is no cauſe <hi>offered</hi> to ſtriue about the greateſt commandement in <hi>Scripture,</hi> nor any new errour of <hi>Religion</hi> brought in, but wee all hold one and the ſame creede of <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo that wee may eaſily agree in one <hi>iudgement,</hi> and deale all zealouſly againſt the common <hi>aduerſary.</hi> From whom how carefully wee ought to <hi>ſeperate</hi> our ſelues I referre you to <hi>Philip Mornay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Morn.</hi> de Eccle. c. 10.</note> that moſt noble <hi>champion</hi> of the truth, in his Tract of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 1. Vſe. <note place="margin">21. Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſt.</note> For the proofe of <hi>many,</hi> who thinke they may be <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in ſhew, and <hi>Papiſts</hi> in deed, frequent our <hi>Churches, Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12287:16"/>and yet keepe their <hi>conſciences</hi> to themſelues; like them in the time of <hi>Optatus; Aliud habet animus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Optatus <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>aliud reſonat ſermo:</hi> They harbour one thing in their hart, and vtter another thing in their <hi>ſpeeches.</hi> But they ſhall find that of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> to be true. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de vita <hi>Chriſ.</hi> ad ſoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem viduam.</note> 
               <hi>Nomen Chriſtiani ille fruſtra ſortitur qui Chriſtum minime imitatur.</hi> It is in vaine for a man to take vpon him the <hi>name</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that doth not <hi>imitate Chriſt.</hi> It is an <hi>abhominable</hi> and <hi>palpable</hi> deuiſe: had <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> done ſo, <note place="margin">Dan. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> had neuer confeſſed the true <hi>power of God.</hi> We muſt not halt betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Baal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 18.21.</note> Hee will be glorified in our <hi>bodies</hi> and <hi>ſoules.</hi> Our <hi>bodyes</hi> are for the <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.13.</note> and wee muſt <hi>loue</hi> him with all our <hi>hearts,</hi> with all our <hi>ſoules,</hi> &amp; with all our <hi>mindes.</hi> He <hi>created</hi> not only the <hi>ſoule,</hi> but alſo the <hi>body,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth the <hi>ſeruice</hi> of both. He hath made <hi>all,</hi> he hath bought <hi>all,</hi> he hath deerely payd for <hi>all,</hi> and therefore muſt haue <hi>all.</hi> O thinke vpon <hi>this</hi> you that bring your <hi>bodyes</hi> to <hi>this,</hi> and the <hi>like places,</hi> (if any ſuch be here) and ſend your <hi>hearts</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> you muſt aunſwere it, may bee this night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>your God: dally</hi> not, <hi>delay</hi> not to caſt away the double minde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hannibal,</hi> when hee had obtained the victory at <hi>Cannas,</hi> if hee had gone ſtraight to <hi>Rome,</hi> by all mens iudgements had taken the Citty, but defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it till the next day, the <hi>Romanes</hi> recouering their forces againe, hee was ſhut out, and heard this approbry:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:12287:17"/>
               <hi>Vincere ſcis</hi> Hanniball, <hi>vti victoria neſcis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou knoweſt how to get the victory, but not how to vſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delayes</hi> inſpirituall matters are much more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: contemne not then the calling of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: <hi>My ſonne giue me thy heart.</hi> It is not <hi>enough</hi> to be outwardly <hi>formall,</hi> ſo much may be <hi>wrought</hi> by the Word in the <hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>wicked:</hi> as it did in <hi>Herod,</hi> working an externall reuerence to <hi>Iohn:</hi> in <hi>Pilate</hi> a diſtraction of minde: in <hi>Agrippa</hi> halfe a reſolution to become a <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> in <hi>Feſtus</hi> a trembling at doomes day: in <hi>Pharaoh</hi> a confeſſion of his ſinnes: but all theſe vaniſhas the <hi>morning dewe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reue. 18.4.</note> O then vtterly forſake <hi>Babylon, Come out of her my</hi> people, <hi>that ye be not</hi> partakers <hi>of her ſinnes, and that yee</hi> receiue <hi>not of her</hi> plagues. For her ſinnes haue reached vnto <hi>Heauen,</hi> and God hath remembred her <hi>iniquities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> If any obiect and ſay, Would you haue vs to <hi>leaue</hi> that Religion wherein our <hi>anceſtours</hi> haue <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> and <hi>died,</hi> and ſome of them ſuffered for?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Wee anſwere, that often men are <hi>blamed</hi> in the Scripture for <hi>walking</hi> in the <hi>wayes</hi> of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> and of others of their anceſtours?</p>
            <p>Often the godly deplore their fathers ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. <note place="margin">1 King. 15.34. Pſal. 106.6. Pſal. 45.11.</note> 
               <hi>Salomons</hi> wife repreſenting the ſpouſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was commanded to <hi>forget</hi> her owne people, and her fathers houſe. VVhat a <hi>praiſe</hi> is it to <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 18. &amp; cap. 21.24.</note> and others, that hauing idolatrous Parents, they rather looked to their <hi>Father</hi> in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:12287:17"/>
If any of them <hi>dyed</hi> in wilfull ignorance, ſhould we for their companie thruſt our ſelues into <hi>Hell?</hi> If any of them were almoſt right, they will not <hi>grudge</hi> that we ſhould haue more <hi>light</hi> opened to vs then they ſaw. <hi>Leauing</hi> the determining ſentence to <hi>Gods</hi> ſecret <hi>iudgement;</hi> there is no doubt but many of them, who liued in the time of <hi>darkeneſſe,</hi> holding <hi>Chriſt</hi> the foundation <hi>aright,</hi> and groning vnder the <hi>heauy burthen</hi> of humane traditions, <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions,</hi> and ſuch Popiſh traſh, by a generall <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> from their errours and aſſured faith in their Sauiour, they found <hi>fauour</hi> with the <hi>Lord,</hi> and for their ſounder part they were of that Church wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee are: Which is the <hi>opinion</hi> of Saynt <hi>Cyprian</hi> in the like caſe; <hi>Deere brother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr.</hi> de ſacr. Domin. cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. Epiſt. 68.</note> 
               <hi>if any of our</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, <hi>eyther ignorantly or ſimply, did not obſerue and holde this which the Lord taught vs to doe by his owne</hi> example <hi>and</hi> miniſtery, <hi>by the</hi> fauour of the Lord, <hi>there may be pardon</hi> giuen to his ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie</p>
            <p>If any <hi>obiect</hi> after this, that ſome of the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt</hi> of our <hi>owne men</hi> were ſometimes affected to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> as, <hi>Luther</hi> was a <hi>Fryer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In vita.</note> and married a <hi>Nunne: Caluin</hi> liued a while vnder <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> gouernours: <hi>Beza</hi> was at firſt addicted to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> poſitions: <hi>Zanchius,</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> both Italianat.</p>
            <p>Let this be graunted, there is no more <hi>preiudice</hi> vnto our <hi>Religion,</hi> or vnto them for this, then that <hi>Moſes</hi> for a time was brought vp as the ſonne of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter: <note place="margin">Exod. 2.10.</note>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 23.6.</note> or that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was borne a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12287:18"/>
               <hi>Phariſee:</hi> or that <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> was a grieuous ſinner: <note place="margin">Luke 8.2.19 2.</note> or <hi>Zaccheus</hi> the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>cuſtome.</hi> It was no fault for <hi>Lot</hi> to come out of <hi>Sodome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.12.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they be blamed that haſten out of <hi>Babylon.</hi> They are bound to <hi>bleſſe God,</hi> who deliuereth them as <hi>Ionah</hi> was freed out of the <hi>Whales</hi> belly: <note place="margin">Iona. 2.10.</note> and as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> reporteth that <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who cauſed the <hi>Iewes</hi> to build the Temple and gaue them backe the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels thereof, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> lib. 11. cap. 1. Antiq. Iud.</note> was moued to doe it by reading the Propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> who 200. yeeres before had named him: <note place="margin">Iſa. 45.1.</note> ſo theſe <hi>looking</hi> into the written word of God, haue beene drawne to the <hi>truth;</hi> ſo was it with that noble ſpirit <hi>Galeacius Caracciolus,</hi> ſonne and heyre apparant to <hi>Calantonius,</hi> Marques of <hi>Vicum</hi> in <hi>Naples,</hi> bred, borne, and brought vp in Popery; a Courtier to the Emperour CHARLES the fift, Nephew to the Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing married to the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Nurimes</hi> daughter, and hauing by her ſixe goodly children, at a Sermon of <hi>Peter Martyrs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza</hi> in vita cius.</note> was firſt touched, after, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Scriptures and other good meanes was fully <hi>conuerted:</hi> hee laboured with his Lady, but could not perſwade her, he forſooke all theſe <hi>allurements,</hi> and for the loue of Chriſt came to <hi>Geneua,</hi> and there liued a <hi>holy</hi> life for forty yeeres, and ſo died. Hee did as <hi>Leui</hi> was commanded to doe by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.9. <hi>He ſayd of father and mother, I haue not ſeene them,</hi> neither did hee acknowledge his <hi>brethren,</hi> nor knew his owne <hi>children.</hi> All <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> muſt be ſuch <hi>Leuites,</hi> regarding neither <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> nor <hi>mother, ſonne</hi> nor <hi>daughter,</hi> in reſpect of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12287:18"/>God.<note place="margin">Gen. 24.56.</note> They muſt ſay as <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seruant to <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> and <hi>Bethuel, Hinder me not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> Vſe 2. <hi>Admonition</hi> to all to be <hi>zealous</hi> and open in the <hi>cauſe</hi> of Religion, neyther fearing the faces of <hi>men,</hi> nor betraying the <hi>cauſe</hi> of GOD vpon any baſe condition.</p>
            <p>I <hi>know,</hi> many haue taxed the zeale of <hi>Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lut.</hi> to. 1.</note> who reſolued to relye onely on the <hi>Scriptures: Si mille Auguſtini,</hi> If a thouſand <hi>Auſtines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. de capt. Bab.</note> or <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſhould perſwade me to any thing, I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hearken to one <hi>Sentence</hi> of the BIBLE: and the Suffrages of two <hi>honeſt men</hi> hauing Scripture, then a whole <hi>Councell.</hi> And his worthy <hi>Reſolution,</hi> who hearing that the Diuines of <hi>Louaine</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> had burned many of his <hi>Bookes</hi> by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Pope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maſſoeus</hi> Chro. 10. p. 273.</note> hee openly burned the <hi>Popes Lawes, Decretals,</hi> and <hi>Buls,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I haue done to them, as they to mee. Re.</hi> 18.6. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox.</hi> Martyrol. Anno 1521. p. 977.</note> And his <hi>Heroicall ſpirit,</hi> daring to <hi>profeſſe</hi> that hee would enter into that fore-warned Citty of <hi>Wormes,</hi> though there had beene as many <hi>Diuels</hi> in their ſtreetes as <hi>Tyles</hi> on their houſes, to anſwere for himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore CHARLES the fift of that name, againſt <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kius</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>But the cauſe was <hi>Gods,</hi> he knew that the <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of GOD was to be got by <hi>violence.</hi> Hee remembred that of CHRIST, <hi>Hee that is not</hi> with <hi>mee, is</hi> againſt <hi>mee: Hee that</hi> gathereth <hi>not with mee,</hi> ſcattereth. Therefore was hee ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt againſt the <hi>Popes head,</hi> and the <hi>Monckes bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Carion</hi> Chro. aucta a <hi>Melanc.</hi> l. 5.</note> which maketh our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> lay ſo many
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12287:19"/>
               <hi>ſlanders</hi> vpon him:<note place="margin">L. 4 Chron.</note>
               <hi>Genebrard</hi> making him the grand <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> becauſe <hi>Luther,</hi> as hee ſaith, in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> maketh 666. but the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> quit him of this <hi>honour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Apoc. 13.18</note> I omit the reſt.</p>
            <p>Yea, <hi>ſuch</hi> was the zeale of Saint <hi>Ierome: If my</hi> Mother <hi>were hanging about my</hi> necke; <hi>if my</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <hi>were on euery ſide,</hi> howling <hi>and</hi> crying; <hi>and if my</hi> Father <hi>were on his</hi> bare <hi>knees, to detaine me in a</hi> wicked life; <hi>I would</hi> ſhake <hi>them off,</hi> deſpiſe <hi>them,</hi> trample <hi>them vnder my feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such,</hi> of <hi>Antonius Marinarius,</hi> hearing that the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> would not haue a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to be certainly perſwaded of his ſaluation: which point, yet <hi>Catharinus</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Minoria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> exam. 1. p. de ſide iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificante.</note> in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then preſent confuted, againſt <hi>Dominicus</hi> of <hi>Soto,</hi> Confeſſor to CHARLES the fift, and one of the <hi>Preſidents;</hi> afterward <hi>Iulius</hi> the third, proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it was not ſufficiently diſcuſſed to decide any thing, hee cryed out; <hi>If</hi> Heauen fall, <hi>if the</hi> Earth vaniſh <hi>away, if the</hi> whole world run head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, <hi>I will looke to the</hi> goodneſſe <hi>of</hi> GOD, <hi>and ſtand</hi> vpright, <hi>and if an</hi> Angell <hi>from heauen ſhall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to</hi> perſwade <hi>me otherwiſe, I will ſay,</hi> Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma <hi>to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh. Checu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> l. de pronunt. lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae Grecae.</note> the zeale of <hi>Thomas Linacer,</hi> who compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the liues of <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> with the 5.6. and 7. Chapters of Saint <hi>Matthewes</hi> Goſpell, cryed out, <hi>Eyther there is no</hi> Goſpell, <hi>or they are no</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such,</hi> of <hi>bleſſed Caluin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> ſo I ſhall euer ſtile them, they would neuer <hi>yeeld</hi> to any King,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12287:19"/>that ſhould draw them from GOD. Their ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may be <hi>wreſted,</hi> but neuer any true <hi>inference</hi> collected that they <hi>pretended</hi> Treaſon. They haue <hi>poyſoned Soules</hi> therefore who by a <hi>Popiſh</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> reconciled, would bring theſe worthy Inſtruments of Gods <hi>Church</hi> within the compaſſe of any bloudy <hi>deſigne.</hi> Let ſuch learne to follow the rule of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> if they haue any <hi>knowledge</hi> to imploy it <hi>in teſtimonium veri, non in adiutorium falſi;</hi> to witneſſe <hi>truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> l. 8. conf. c. 8.</note> not to helpe <hi>falſhood.</hi> Let them <hi>remember</hi> that of <hi>Aug. Surgunt indocti, &amp;c.</hi> The vnlearned who vpon a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience were zealous for the <hi>truth,</hi> ſhall riſe vp in Iudgement againſt ſuch, and get <hi>Heauen</hi> from them. Let not them that liue of the <hi>Altar,</hi> liue ftom the <hi>Altar,</hi> but preach <hi>truth</hi> in <hi>ſeaſon</hi> and out of <hi>ſeaſon:</hi> and if euer wee had ſtrength to rattle out the <hi>terrible</hi> Iudgements of GOD againſt ſinne, let vs now doe it. Let the light of our liues ſhine in the <hi>faces</hi> of the world. Let vs <hi>diuide</hi> the word <hi>aright,</hi> for curſed is hee that doth the <hi>worke</hi> of the Lord <hi>negligently.</hi> I ſay to <hi>Archippus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 48.</note> Let him take heed to the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> that hee hath receiued in the Lord, <note place="margin">Col. 4.</note> that hee fulfill it. Take heede, looke vnto it. Giue good and carefull <hi>regard:</hi> haue your eyes in your <hi>heads,</hi> and your <hi>hearts</hi> in your <hi>Eye-lids.</hi> It is a <hi>worke,</hi> a <hi>burthen,</hi> a <hi>ſeruice,</hi> rather then a <hi>Play,</hi> or <hi>honour,</hi> or <hi>vacancy.</hi> Wee haue <hi>receiued</hi> it of him, that will require it, <hi>talent</hi> and <hi>vſe, principall</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> and giue vs the <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of his <hi>wrath,</hi> if wee doe it to <hi>halfes</hi> and not wholy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12287:20"/>
Let vs <hi>not be</hi> as children, <hi>toſſed to and fro, and carried about with</hi> euery winde of <hi>Doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they lye in waite to <hi>deceiue.</hi> But ſpeaking the truth, in loue, let vs grow vp into him, in all <hi>things,</hi> which is the <hi>head,</hi> euen <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For it is almoſt all one, ſaith <hi>Fulgentius</hi> in his firſt booke to <hi>Thraſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> King of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> to deny the <hi>faith,</hi> and not <hi>maintane</hi> it. His <hi>reaſon</hi> is, becauſe by <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame ſilence</hi> he ſtrengthneth <hi>errour,</hi> who through feare or negligence holding his peace, affirmeth not the <hi>truth,</hi> like a ſleepy <hi>centenar,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the tents of his <hi>Captaine,</hi> not that he hath a will perhaps to <hi>betray</hi> them, but becauſe hee keepeth not the <hi>watch</hi> as hee ought, nor <hi>deſcrieth</hi> the enemie which <hi>commeth</hi> to aſſault them.</p>
            <p>Looke vpon the auncient <hi>Fathers of the</hi> Church, how voluminous they were, <hi>dealing</hi> againſt <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques,</hi> and defending true religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origen,</hi> liuing Anno domini 240. leauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him 1000. treatiſes, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> catal. de viris Illuſtr.</note> almoſt all periſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Anno 380. 3. <hi>volumes,</hi> extant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſoſtum,</hi> Anno 411. 5. <hi>tomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ierom,</hi> Anno 420. 9. <hi>tomes. Auguſtine,</hi> at the ſame time, 9. <hi>volumes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, Anno 600. 6. <hi>tomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea our owne worthyes may ſtirre vs vp, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cochleus</hi> hiſt. de <hi>Huſſitis</hi> l. 1.</note>
               <hi>Wicklif,</hi> who wrote workes as great in quantitie as S. <hi>Auſtins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luther,</hi> who wrote 12. <hi>tomes. Eraſmus,</hi> 9. <hi>tomes,</hi> beſides his notes vpon many of the Fathers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gualther</hi> 15. <hi>tomes. Brentius</hi> 8. <hi>tomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:12287:20"/>
               <hi>Caluin,</hi> 13. <hi>tomes, Zanchius,</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>I reckon not the <hi>labours</hi> of latter, as memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for ſome things, <hi>Fox, Iewel, Whitakers, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phreys, Perkins,</hi> Docter <hi>Raynolds,</hi> Docter <hi>Abbots,</hi> Docter <hi>Moorten,</hi> Docter <hi>Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs all <hi>looke</hi> vpon the zeale of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the Primitiue Church, who being daily <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> yet prayed vnto God, and prayſed the <hi>Lord,</hi> in the dens of the <hi>Earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin.</hi> ſecund. l. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. 61.</note> as <hi>Plinius ſecundus</hi> their aduerſary in the time of <hi>Traians</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth of them. But <hi>wee,</hi> beloued, haue our <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories open,</hi> our <hi>Pulpits frequented,</hi> our <hi>Churches beautified.</hi> They had the <hi>greateſt</hi> tormentors that euer were, and yet <hi>inſulted</hi> ouer them, <note place="margin">In an Epiſtle to the Aſians.</note> as <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Pius,</hi> the beſt of the Heathen Emperours, <hi>confeſſed.</hi> Wee haue had <hi>Kings</hi> to be our nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Queenes</hi> to be our nurſing <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider the three <hi>Children</hi> ſinging in the <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace; Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> in the <hi>ſtockes, Martyrs</hi> at the <hi>ſtake;</hi> other holy <hi>Saints</hi> deuoured by <hi>wilde Beaſts, beheaded, preſſed, roſted</hi> vpon ſpits, <hi>broyled on</hi> grid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>irons, <hi>boyled</hi> in hot Oyle, and ſcalding Leade; <hi>throwne</hi> downe from Mountaines vpon ſharpe ſtakes, <hi>torne</hi> with wilde horſes, <hi>rent aſunder</hi> with the violence of bowed trees, <hi>brayned, racked, prickt</hi> with pen-kniues, their eyes <hi>boared</hi> out, their tongues <hi>cut,</hi> their Armes, Hands, Legs, Feete, and all their members <hi>disfigured,</hi> their bowels <hi>diſmembred,</hi> and they famiſhed to death, yet neuer denying their <hi>religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:12287:21"/>
Behold the <hi>Martyrs</hi> in <hi>Queene</hi> MARIES time, thruſt out of their <hi>Houſes,</hi> ſpoyled of their <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> loaded with <hi>irons,</hi> locked in <hi>Priſons,</hi> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with <hi>fire.</hi> They were <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bloud,</hi> as well as wee; life was as <hi>ſweet</hi> to them as to vs, their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were as <hi>ſenſible</hi> of paine as ours; wee goe to the ſame <hi>Heauen</hi> with them, yet to ſee how they <hi>dyed,</hi> would make a man out of <hi>loue</hi> with life, and out of all <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>death:</hi> it would extract <hi>teares</hi> from any that was euer able to <hi>weepe.</hi> Beloued, there is now no <hi>dragging</hi> out of <hi>houſes,</hi> no <hi>hiding</hi> of <hi>bibles,</hi> no <hi>creeping</hi> into <hi>woods,</hi> no <hi>rotting</hi> in <hi>dungeons,</hi> no <hi>caſting</hi> of <hi>infants</hi> out of the mothers belly into the <hi>flames:</hi> the Goſpel is <hi>preached, profeſſed, Profeſſors en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, Preachers rewarded.</hi> Neuer was the <hi>Land</hi> ſo happy for zealous and preaching <hi>Biſhops:</hi> neuer <hi>better meanes</hi> of ſaluation offered. O then, let vs be <hi>feruent in ſpirit,</hi> ſeruing the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It was this that <hi>honoured Apollos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.11.</note>
               <hi>Act.</hi> 18.25. Let vs not ſell the truth for the <hi>fauour of men.</hi> Let vs remember that <hi>Eli</hi> was <hi>plagued</hi> for honouring his <hi>Children</hi> aboue GOD: <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18.</note> ſo, all muſt looke for ſome iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that are neyther <hi>cold</hi> nor <hi>hot,</hi> but <hi>neglect</hi> the worke of the LORD. Be eyther a whole <hi>Proteſtant</hi> or <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not for any to defend that <hi>Atheiſticall</hi> Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that all <hi>Controuerſies</hi> may be taken vp, and all Religions accord together; that our <hi>Differences</hi> are of ſmall <hi>importance;</hi> that they pertaine onely to learned men to thinke vpon; it is not for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people to talke of <hi>Religion;</hi> yes, euery one
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12287:21"/>muſt be ready to giue an account of his <hi>Faith,</hi> and yeeld a reaſon of his <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> and dye in defence of his <hi>Religion:</hi> eſpecially, ſeeing <hi>luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſse</hi> is here <hi>threatned.</hi> And therefore were I as <hi>happy</hi> as <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings. 3.5.</note> to haue whatſoeuer I would aske, this is the greateſt <hi>bleſsing</hi> that I would <hi>craue</hi> for you, to be <hi>zealous</hi> and <hi>amend,</hi> and doe your <hi>firſt workes,</hi> and this ſhall be my Prayer: but I come to <hi>Chriſts</hi> threat of the Hypocrite.</p>
            <q>So then, becauſe thou art luke warme, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>IT was a wiſe <hi>Anſwere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1<hi rend="sup">a</hi>.2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>.</note> that is reported of our beſt, and I hope the laſt Cardinall, that this Iſland ſhall euer ſee, who when a skilfull <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> vpon the Calculation of his <hi>Natiuitie</hi> had fore-told him ſome <hi>ſpecialties</hi> concerning his future <hi>eſtate,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: ſuch perhaps I was borne, but ſince that time, I haue beene <hi>borne againe,</hi> and my <hi>ſecond na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitte</hi> hath croſſed my <hi>firſt.</hi> It was otherwiſe with <hi>Laodicea,</hi> for at <hi>firſt</hi> it was a <hi>holy</hi> Citie, a <hi>choſen</hi> place, a <hi>iuſt</hi> people, but now they <hi>reuolted, apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtated,</hi> and the beſt of them were <hi>hypocrites, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme,</hi> neyther <hi>hot</hi> nor <hi>cold,</hi> therefore GOD threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>So then, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Victorinus</hi> interpreteth <hi>luke-warmneſſe</hi> of <hi>diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers</hi> of <hi>Religion, Polititians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Primaſius,</hi> of <hi>rich men</hi> vnmercifull to the <hi>poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> of them that haue <hi>Faith,</hi> and no <hi>workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12287:22"/>
               <hi>Anſbertus,</hi> of many who tooke the <hi>habite</hi> of <hi>Monkes,</hi> but followed the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rupertus,</hi> of vnthankefull men attributing all to <hi>themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioachimus Abbas,</hi> of one that is neyther <hi>triſtis ad poenitentiam,</hi> nor <hi>alacer ad Dei obſequium,</hi> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the <hi>ſorrowfull</hi> in <hi>repentance,</hi> nor <hi>quicke</hi> in the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Coelius Pannonius,</hi> of <hi>Hypocrites</hi> counterfeiting vertues which they haue not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Generally,</hi> it is vnderſtood of <hi>thoſe,</hi> who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelues to be good when they are bad, as the <hi>Phariſees. Iohn</hi> 9.40. who though they <hi>ſaw</hi> CHRIST in <hi>perſon,</hi> and beheld him in his <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> yet they would not <hi>acknowledge</hi> him; they were <hi>blinde,</hi> yet ſeemed to be vnwilling of this veyle, <hi>Are wee blinde alſo?</hi> it was hypocriſie in them.</p>
            <p>When this once poſſeſſeth a man, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ber.</hi> ſe. 65. Cant.</note> the <hi>Spirit</hi> is <hi>quenched, Sloath</hi> then <hi>increaſeth, Charitie cooleth, Pleaſure flattereth, Securitie decemeth, Cuſtome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noketh,</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> is <hi>diſſembled, right</hi> is <hi>concealed,</hi> and the <hi>feare</hi> of GOD <hi>relinquiſhed:</hi> this is the <hi>end</hi> of luke-warmneſſe, and the <hi>fruit</hi> is the wrath of the <hi>Almighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>So then becauſe, &amp;c.]</hi> Whence this <hi>Doctrine</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; <hi>Luke-warmneſſe in Religion moueth the Higheſt to great wrath.</hi> A ſinne ſo <hi>horrible,</hi> that the Lord threatneth, if any man in <hi>faint-heartedneſſe</hi> for want of Patience with-draw himſelfe, his ſoule ſhall haue no pleaſure in him. <note place="margin">He. 10.38.</note> And the fearefull
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12287:22"/>and <hi>vnbeleeuing,</hi> (which dare not ſtand to the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion</hi> of the truth) ſhall haue their portion among <hi>murtherers,</hi> and <hi>whoremongers,</hi> and <hi>ſorcerers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 21.8.</note> and ſuch like <hi>perſons,</hi> in the Lake which <hi>burneth</hi> with fire and Brimſtone, which is the <hi>ſecond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee muſt haue our <hi>Fathers</hi> name written in our <hi>foreheads,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 14 1.</note> that all the world may ſee wee are not <hi>aſhamed</hi> of our <hi>profeſsion.</hi> If we be not <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> yet we muſt be <hi>confeſſors,</hi> elſe we are no <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> So <hi>Barnard, Cum cauſa Dei ventilater in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium &amp; falſitas praeponitur veritati, qui pro perſona quam gerit non reſiſtit, de ſuo damnabitur ſilentio.</hi> When the cauſe of God is <hi>diſcuſsed,</hi> and falſehood <hi>preferred</hi> before the <hi>truth,</hi> hee that according to the <hi>perſon</hi> hee beareth, doth not reſiſt it, ſhall bee <hi>condemned</hi> for his ſilence.</p>
            <p>Wee all ſtand vpon <hi>Iaacobs Ladder,</hi> and muſt eyther <hi>aſcend</hi> or <hi>deſcend;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bar.</hi> epiſt. 91.</note>
               <hi>Si attentes ſtare ruas ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt,</hi> If thou trye to ſtand ſtill, thou muſt fall; he is no whit good that deſireth not to be better: for when a man leaueth his deſire of being better then hee giueth ouer his former <hi>goodneſſe.</hi> So <hi>Ier. Vbicoeperimus ſtare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. <hi>epiſt. ad</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metriadem de Virginitate.</note>
               <hi>deſcendimus, noſtrumque non progredi iam regredi eſt.</hi> When we begin to ſtand, ſtill, we goe downe, and our not going <hi>forward,</hi> is to goe <hi>backward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is recorded of <hi>Valentinian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theod.</hi> l. c. 4.</note> that when his <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> had choſen him to be <hi>Emperour,</hi> they were conſulting to haue another ioyned with him: <hi>No</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>it was in your power to giue me the</hi> Empyre <hi>while I had it not, but now when I haue it, it is not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12287:23"/>in your power to giue me a</hi> partner. VVe gaue God our hearts in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and they belong to <hi>him</hi> by right of <hi>creation.</hi> He will haue the whole and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure any riuals or luke-warmneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>6</label> The <hi>vſe</hi> of this toucheth to the quicke all thoſe who <hi>imagine</hi> that they may do as others in outward worſhip, ſo that they <hi>keepe</hi> their hearts to God, as though GOD were not the creatour of their <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> as well as of their <hi>ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some are like the <hi>world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Optat.</hi> l. 1.</note> running in a <hi>Circle</hi> of temporizing; alwayes about the <hi>way,</hi> neuer in the <hi>way:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim 3.7.</note> like thoſe ſeely women, euer <hi>learning,</hi> neuer comming to the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Truth.</hi> Others, like the <hi>Hedge-hogge,</hi> which hath two holes, one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>South,</hi> another toward the <hi>North;</hi> the wind blowing in the one, ſhee <hi>ſhutteth</hi> that, and <hi>openeth</hi> the other; they turne on any ſide. Others, like <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> that came to <hi>Ieſus</hi> to be inſtructed, but it was by night: <note place="margin">Ioh. 3 1. Ioh. 9.28.</note> like <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple of Ieſus, but ſecretly, fearing the Iewes. Like the <hi>Marygold,</hi> ſhutting and opening with the Sunne. Like <hi>Mermayds,</hi> halfe Fleſh halfe Fiſh. I would to God wee were eyther <hi>cold</hi> or <hi>hot,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hot and <hi>zealous in Religion,</hi> that as the hotteſt <hi>regions</hi> bring forth ſweeteſt ſpices, ſo the moſt <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> people might be moſt <hi>fruitfull</hi> in good works. But alas, many amongſt vs the more they are taught, the more ignorant they are, and the more <hi>aged</hi> the more <hi>colde.</hi> Many come to heare the word, but they profit not in the encreaſe of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge they will come and ſtand before the <hi>Preacher,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:12287:23"/>but they will not trye by the <hi>Scripture</hi> whether the things be ſo, or not, which are taught them. They will not be at coſt to buy a <hi>Bible,</hi> or if they doe, they will not read it, or if ſometimes, yet not in a conſtant courſe.</p>
            <p>Many are content to frequent the <hi>publike</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations vpon the Sabbath, but they will not priuately <hi>ſanctifie</hi> it in their <hi>families.</hi> Many will ſhew <hi>religion</hi> in the generall calling of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> while they are in the Church, but in their <hi>particular</hi> duties they faile. Theſe are the ſinnes that goe vp vnto <hi>Heauen,</hi> and cry for <hi>vengeance,</hi> and threaten <hi>puniſhments.</hi> What could haue taken away that ſweet <hi>Prince,</hi> of freſh and bleeding <hi>memory,</hi> Prince HENRY, the expectation of all the Chriſtian world, but our <hi>luke-warmneſſe?</hi> But bleſſed Prince, our ſinnes haue aduantaged thy holy <hi>ſoule,</hi> though robbed vs of our happineſſe in thee. O <hi>mourne</hi> then for the ſinnes of this <hi>age,</hi> but eſpecially for <hi>luke warmneſse.</hi> Returne ye ſeduced ſoules from the fleſhpots of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> from the vanities of <hi>Rome,</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to God the ſacrifice of <hi>zeale</hi> in defence of our true Church.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall ſay, wee loue to be <hi>zealous</hi> for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, and not for noueltie; your Church hath beene but ſince <hi>Luther, Anno Dom.</hi> 1517. for this is a common obiection.</p>
            <p>Wee anſwere,<note place="margin">D. <hi>Abbot.</hi> Now the moſt reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> anſwere to D. <hi>Hill.</hi>
               </note> hee was not the <hi>founder of our Religion,</hi> but God himſelfe, the <hi>auncient</hi> of dayes. As he did <hi>originally</hi> deduce thoſe things which hee taught againſt <hi>Papiſtry</hi> from the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and out
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12287:24"/>of the <hi>workes</hi> of the <hi>auncient Fathers,</hi> ſo did hee deriue them hereditarilie from others, as <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Guic.</hi> hiſt. l. 13.</note>
               <hi>Hierome of Prage,</hi> and the reſt as <hi>Francis Guicciardin</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>Florentine Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher</hi> plainely confeſſeth. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox.</hi> Martirall.</note>
               <hi>Hus</hi> being 100. yeeres before <hi>Luther,</hi> and yet prophecying of him not long before his death.</p>
            <p>And ſo generally, was his Doctrine ſpred, that a generall counſell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In tab concil. ante <hi>Platinae.</hi> hiſt.</note> was called princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally againſt the <hi>Huſsites.</hi> The nobles of <hi>Bohemia</hi> wrote ſupplications for them, <note place="margin">Anno 1415.</note> but (contrary to the <hi>Emperours</hi> ſafe conduct giuen to the former of them) they were <hi>burnt. Sigiſmund</hi> could not bee ſatisfied for the breaking of his promiſe, till by their decree which is in the 10. Seſſion, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſignified that their authoritie was ſuch, that they might diſannull what he had appointed. <hi>Campian</hi> ſhifteth it of ſo. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Camp.</hi> cat. 4.</note>
               <hi>Imperator promiſit, orbis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus maior Imperatore diſſoluit.</hi> He calleth ſome <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> the Chriſtian <hi>world,</hi> were they neuer ſo many in number, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cochl.</hi> hiſt. <hi>Huſſ.</hi> lib. 2. p. 74.</note> had they authoritie to make him breake his Oath? At laſt they muſt flye to their olde <hi>axiome.</hi> Faith is not to be kept with <hi>Heretikes,</hi> The <hi>Heathens</hi> would be aſhamed of it, and <hi>Cacanza</hi> paſſeth it ouer being in the 10. Seſſion: ſaying, <hi>Nothing was done then worthie of note.</hi> I omit their taking the Cup from the people, a <hi>non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante</hi> of <hi>Ch. Com. Seſſ.</hi> 13. Before theſe <hi>Wiclif</hi> was zealous for our <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſo earneſt againſt Popery, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cochl.</hi> l. 2.</note> that <hi>Cochleus</hi> affirmeth, Hee thinketh the torments of <hi>Wiclif</hi> are greater in Hell then thoſe of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12287:24"/>
               <hi>Iudas</hi> or <hi>Nero.</hi> Heare the charitie of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> towards the beſt <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> His <hi>Doctrine</hi> was ſo generally receiued in <hi>Oxford</hi> by the beſt, that Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the eleuenth, in the yeere 1378. directed his Bull to that <hi>Vniuerſitie</hi> againſt his articles. Yea, for the ſpace of 30. yeeres after, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Huſſus.</hi> to. 1. in replica. contra. <hi>Ioh. Stoakes</hi> foll. 110.</note> ſcarſe was there a man there but held his <hi>opinions,</hi> and taught the ſame to their ſchollers. He hauing proteſted, that as neere as hee could, hee did all things <hi>ad honorem Dei &amp; vtilitatem Eccleſiae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De verit. ſcrip.</hi> p. 145. &amp; p. 15.</note> For the glory of God and benefit of his Church.</p>
            <p>They were ſtill defended, in the dayes of <hi>King Edward</hi> the fourth, Anno 1476. which cauſed the <hi>King</hi> to write letters for the burning of them. I might alledge the teſtimonies of many, <hi>Reignald Paine,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> and others, Anno 1457. out of this place, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Balaeus</hi> cent. c. 19.</note> Preaching that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſinned in buying their admiſſions of the <hi>Pope,</hi> againſt begging <hi>Fryers, Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and other <hi>errours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ge other ſtoryes at large, of the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> burned in S. <hi>Gyles</hi> field, <hi>Anno</hi> 1417. in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our Religion. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox.</hi> to. 1.</note> Of <hi>Humphrey</hi> Duke of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter, Sonne of HENRY the fourth, Brother of HENRY the fift, and Vncle to HENRY the ſixt, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Balaeus</hi> cent. 8. c. 2.</note> ſtifled with a <hi>pillow</hi> for profeſſion of the <hi>Goſpell, Anno</hi> 1447. ſo that before and after <hi>Luther,</hi> wee haue had <hi>champions</hi> to fight againſt the Pope. If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is hath not alwayes beene viſible, wee anſwere, no more is alwayes the Moone in the heauens, becauſe <hi>ſometimes</hi> there is none <hi>ſeene,</hi> as in the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12287:25"/>change, yet it were abſurd to conclude that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no Moone at all there.</p>
            <p>The auncient <hi>Fathers</hi> before theſe, were ours in the maine <hi>points</hi> of religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactantius,</hi> againſt images. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>inſtit. c.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> againſt praying to <hi>Saints. com. in Rom. c.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſoſtom,</hi> for the marriage of the <hi>Clergie. hom.</hi> 7. <hi>ep. Heb. &amp; l.</hi> 1. <hi>adu.</hi> Iouin.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Six. Sen. Bib. 8. l. 5.</note> againſt free will, made <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> reiect his opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodoret,</hi> againſt <hi>tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſo that he who in the end of his dialogues, writeth the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the Reader, is enforced though he be a <hi>Papist</hi> to confeſſe that hee hath many things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. Poſt <hi>Epiph. The:</hi> dial.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory,</hi> againſt the Supremacie of the <hi>Pope. Ep. ad Plauritium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barnard,</hi> touching the matter of <hi>merit by works. ſe.</hi> 61. <hi>in cant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>iuſtification</hi> by faith in Chriſt alone. <hi>ep.</hi> 190. for certaine aſſurance of <hi>Saluation,</hi> in the death, and by the ſtrength of our <hi>Sauiour. ſe.</hi> 3. <hi>de</hi> 7. <hi>miſericordijs.</hi> And for diſliking then the vile life of the Clergie, <hi>ſe. in concilio Rhemenſi:</hi> how copious is he?</p>
            <p>But wee ſtand not vpon the authorities of men, neither vpon the name of <hi>Lutherans, Caluiniſts, Zuinglians:</hi> for theſe were not founders of our <hi>Church,</hi> but reformers of it, and ſweepers of many abuſes and <hi>Popiſh errours:</hi> Neither ſo much vpon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12287:25"/>the name of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> though this name aroſe honourably at <hi>Spires</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> when the <hi>Duke Electour of Saxony,</hi> the <hi>Marques</hi> of <hi>Brandeburge,</hi> the <hi>Lantſgraue</hi> and other <hi>Princes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sleid.</hi> Hiſt. l. 6.</note> made a ſolemne proteſtation againſt an edict made in <hi>preiudice</hi> of the reformed Religion, <hi>Anno</hi> 1529. But with matureſt iudgement, and ſober <hi>vnderstanding,</hi> our men conferre the <hi>Scripture</hi> in many languages, they pray vnto God to inlighten them, they looke into <hi>Fathers, Hiſtories, Councels,</hi> they compare old <hi>things</hi> with <hi>new,</hi> they leaue no good meanes <hi>vnattempted</hi> to ſift and ſound the truth, and ſtill the farther they looke, the leſſe ground they finde for <hi>Popery:</hi> they more hate it in their old age, then in their young, vnleſſe they put a vayle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>eyes;</hi> then let them be <hi>carried,</hi> and run from vs, they were <hi>neuer of</hi> vs.</p>
            <p>Nay, the <hi>bookes</hi> of controuerſie in Religion, ſo they be not mingled with State-<hi>cauſes,</hi> are to be ſold commonly, which yet our <hi>aduerſaries</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict to their <hi>followers:</hi> and which is more the <hi>ſcripture</hi> is open, euery man may <hi>read it,</hi> and is exhorted to the <hi>ſtudy</hi> of it, to lay foundation here as vpon a <hi>Rocke:</hi> not to build vpon the <hi>waters,</hi> the Scholemen, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doe. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ferdinand. Velloſill.</hi> Ep. in praef. in aduerſ. Schol. Theol.</note> Witneſſe one of their owne writers, who teſtifieth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he had ſtudied <hi>Schole-Diuinitie</hi> and the Canon law for the ſpace of 16. <hi>yeeres,</hi> and yet neuer ſo much as ſaluted either the <hi>Scriptures</hi> or <hi>Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that our <hi>Aduerſaries</hi> are <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12287:26"/>colde nor hot, and come firſt here to be <hi>taxed.</hi> For doe they not perſwade themſelues that they are <hi>rich,</hi> when they are <hi>poore,</hi> and <hi>blind,</hi> and <hi>naked</hi> in ſpirituall graces, counting Chriſts <hi>robes</hi> of righteouſneſſe not <hi>large</hi> enough to couer their <hi>nakedneſſe</hi> of ſinne, <note place="margin">Iſ. 64.6.</note> patching to a piece of <hi>new cloth,</hi> as if the old were out-worne, botching to it the <hi>menſtruous</hi> and <hi>filthy</hi> clouts of their owne <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> which like the curtald <hi>garments</hi> of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants cannot hide their ſhame, <note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.4.</note> but <hi>defile</hi> them, as <hi>Iob</hi> confeſſed, <note place="margin">Iob 9.31.</note>
               <hi>Mine owne garments defile mee,</hi> and had more <hi>need</hi> to be waſhed themſelues in the <hi>blood</hi> of the <hi>Lambe,</hi> then to goe about to <hi>wipe</hi> away their ſcarlet <hi>ſinnes</hi> by <hi>Popiſh</hi> Indulgences?</p>
            <p>Were Saint <hi>Paul</hi> now in <hi>Rome</hi> hee would vtter the ſame <hi>words</hi> that hee did in the midſt of <hi>Mars hill</hi> at <hi>Athens; I ſee that in all things you are too</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious <hi>and</hi> furious: for, as CHRIST was <hi>crucified</hi> at <hi>Rome, Re.</hi> 11.8. which is not meant in reſpect of the <hi>place,</hi> for that was <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but if wee reſpect the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authoritie</hi> that put him to death, a <hi>Romane</hi> Iudge, <hi>Romane</hi> Lawes, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> authoritie, a kinde of death proper to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,</hi> and in a place which then was within the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire: ſo, now in his members hee is eſpecially perſecuted by <hi>Rome;</hi> ſending out <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> as ſo many <hi>Fire-brands,</hi> ſeeking to ſet on <hi>fire</hi> the ſeuerall corners of the Church: but theſe and the reſt of thoſe <hi>Orders,</hi> are at laſt <hi>betrayed</hi> by their owne Confederates.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Albertus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sleid.</hi> l. 21.</note>
               <hi>Pightus,</hi> and <hi>Ferus,</hi> and <hi>Vergerius,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:12287:26"/>who intended to write againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> in the point of Iuſtification by Faith onely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Didacus de la Vega,</hi> a Spaniſh Fryer of <hi>Toledo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Do. 12. poſt Pentecoſt.</note> in the <hi>ſufficiencie</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Andreas Maſius,</hi> in Reliques.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Contarenus</hi> the Cardinall,<note place="margin">De lib. arbit.</note> touching the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Free-will.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">De reformat. Eccleſiae.</note>By <hi>Petrus de Aliaco,</hi> in the Canonizing of ſo many Saints.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Seculars,</hi> withſtanding the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quod l. fol. 21 In margine.</note> who giue a toleration to their <hi>Proſelytes</hi> to come to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches.</p>
            <p>Alas, what zeale is in this, or in their other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? yet to giue them their due, I muſt confeſſe they haue <hi>zeale,</hi> but not according to <hi>knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How <hi>zealous</hi> are they to the <hi>Pope,</hi> in their reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and worſhip of him? The word <hi>Papa</hi> at the firſt vſed honeſtly for a Father, as <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſtileth <hi>Ierome,</hi> but now challenged by an <hi>vſurper, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer,</hi> and <hi>Herodian Fox;</hi> and more truſt giuen to <hi>him,</hi> then to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Gerſon</hi> in his time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gerſon.</hi> part. 1. de exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. doct. confid. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>Treaſons</hi> dare they not attempt to <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> his Kingdome? witneſſe the <hi>Gun-pouder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> for which prayers were made by <hi>R. B. P.</hi> in his <hi>Seauen ſparkes of the enkindled Soule,</hi> before the <hi>Stratagem</hi> was diſcouered; and his <hi>Motto, In my Meditation breaketh out fire;</hi> His <hi>brag, The memory of Nouelties ſhall periſh with a</hi> cracke, p. 32. <hi>The tempeſtuous</hi> night <hi>being paſſed, a perpetuall</hi> day <hi>ſhall be our comfort,</hi> p. 35. <hi>The</hi> cracke <hi>was heard into all
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12287:27"/>Lands, and made Nations quake for feare,</hi> p. 54. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the hearts of thoſe thy Labourers: endue them with ſtrength from aboue, and giue ſucceſſe vnto their endeuors,</hi> p. 69. <hi>Parſenimus</hi> defends it, ſaying, <hi>Take away roote and branch.</hi> So, <hi>Eudaemon-Iohannes,</hi> apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gizing <hi>Garnet,</hi> but as ſufficiently anſwered as euer our Church could deſire, <note place="margin">D. <hi>Abbot.</hi>
               </note> by a reuerend <hi>Prelate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What damnable <hi>ſlanders</hi> haue they not put vpon our late <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> bleſſed <hi>Queene</hi> ELIZABETH: they haue it from their Father, <hi>Parſons,</hi> I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid, the <hi>Diuell;</hi> for who elſe could <hi>breathe</hi> out ſuch impoſtumate detractions againſt <hi>her,</hi> who was the <hi>glory</hi> her Sexe, the Myrrour of <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> whom all Proteſtant <hi>Generations</hi> ſhall euer call <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> though a generation of <hi>Vipers,</hi> not <hi>fore-warned</hi> of vengeance to come vpon <hi>them,</hi> ſeeke to ſting her <hi>reputation,</hi> calling her <hi>miſeram foemina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> placing her in <hi>Hell;</hi> making her life <hi>wicked,</hi> her death <hi>curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He <hi>dipped</hi> his pen in the <hi>poyſon</hi> of <hi>Aſpes,</hi> which was vnder his <hi>lips,</hi> and ſought to enuenome the <hi>name</hi> of this holy Saint, whom <hi>neighbouring</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons eyther <hi>triumphed</hi> in, or <hi>trembled</hi> at; whoſe <hi>countenance</hi> was able to terrifie <hi>Treaſon,</hi> who might truely haue vſed the words of <hi>Deborah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 5.8.</note>
               <hi>In Iſrael, vntill I</hi> Deborah <hi>came vp, they choſe new Gods,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe gouernment all this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>you of this place,</hi> liued in ſuch peace and plenty, in ſuch obedience to GOD and <hi>her,</hi> and in ſuch loue one to another. She was a woman after Gods owne <hi>heart,</hi> ſhee led his people like a <hi>Flocke</hi> 45. <hi>yeeres</hi> through a Wilderneſſe of many <hi>diſtreſsfull
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12287:27"/>dangers;</hi> ſhee was the <hi>Diamond</hi> in the Ring of the <hi>Monarchs</hi> of the earth, and notwithſtanding all the <hi>roarings</hi> of the Buls of <hi>Baſan,</hi> Centaurs and Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurs of <hi>Rome,</hi> their <hi>thundrings, lightnings, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, execrations, Incantations, conſpiracies, rebellions, drugs, daggers,</hi> and <hi>dags,</hi> yet ſhe liued to out-liue the malice of her enemies, and dyed in <hi>peace,</hi> and was buried with <hi>Regall buriall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the <hi>zeale</hi> of theſe prouoke vs, leaſt they get ground of vs in their bad cauſe: it is good to be zealous in a good cauſe; <hi>Canes latrant pro dominis,</hi> Dogges barke in defence of their <hi>Maſters,</hi> and ſhall wee be <hi>ſilent</hi> in defending the <hi>Lord</hi> IESVS. Feare not the ſcoffes of <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> thou art a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at home, no maruell if the Dogs of the world barke at thee. There is none that reproacheth thee for zeale in <hi>Religion,</hi> but brandeth himſelfe with the ſinne of <hi>luke-warmneſſe,</hi> and here hee may ſee his puniſhment. <hi>Woe be to fearefull hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 2.12.</note>
               <hi>and faint hands, and the ſinner that goeth two wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs that thinke we ſtand take heede leaſt we fall: let vs conſider the <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> redeeme the <hi>time,</hi> not harden our <hi>hearts,</hi> hearken to the <hi>voyce</hi> of GOD while it is called to <hi>day.</hi> GOD ſpared not the olde <hi>world,</hi> who deſpiſed <hi>Noah;</hi> the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> which vexed <hi>Lot; Ieruſalem,</hi> which abuſed the <hi>Prophets;</hi> and you heare how hee threatneth LAODICEA. How ſhall wee eſcape if wee neglect ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? Hee will <hi>ſhew</hi> vs our of his mouth if wee diſſemble before him. Let vs then now at the laſt <hi>ſeparate</hi> light from darknes, God from an <hi>Idoll,</hi> the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12287:28"/>the Iſraelites from the Canaanites, the precious from the vile, the beleeuers from Infidels, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants from Papiſts. Let them <hi>returne</hi> vnto vs, but let not vs <hi>returne</hi> vnto them, who in <hi>Superſtition</hi> are Heatheniſh, in <hi>Tradition</hi> Iewiſh, in <hi>Treaſon</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelliſh. Then ſhall hee make vs to this <hi>people,</hi> a fenced <hi>brazen</hi> wall, and they ſhall <hi>fight</hi> againſt vs, but ſhall not <hi>preuaile</hi> againſt vs; <hi>for I am with thee to ſaue thee and deliuer thee, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my laſt <hi>circumſtance</hi> calleth mee.</p>
            <p>The Iewes had three kindes of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,<note place="margin">21.22. <hi>Druſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> Heb. quaeſt. l. 1. &amp; 2.</note>
               <hi>Niddui, Herem, Sham-meth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the firſt they were remoued from <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> aſſemblies. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> By the ſecond there was an <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema</hi> publiſhed againſt them. By the third they were <hi>Samatized:</hi> the word <hi>Sham-matha</hi> in the <hi>Chalde</hi> or according to the <hi>Hebrew Sham</hi> &amp; <hi>Meth. Hi</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying there is death. So is there in this <hi>ſeperation,</hi> The Lord <hi>willingly</hi> freeth himſelfe of them, as a man would his <hi>ſtomack</hi> of <hi>vndigeſted meat:</hi> He doth it with a kinde of <hi>exultation.</hi> This <hi>Moyſes</hi> tolde the <hi>rebellious</hi> Iſraelites: and it ſhall come to paſſe that as the Lord reioyced ouer you to doe you good, and to multiply you; ſo the Lord will reioyce ouer you to deſtroy you, and to bring you to <hi>nought,</hi> and ye ſhall be plucked from the land whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goeſt to poſſeſſe it. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.63. And if once the Lord caſt vs vp, hee will neuer returne to his <hi>vomit,</hi> but I preſſe not the word: I come to my laſt Doctrine.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:12287:28"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> The long ſuffering of <hi>God</hi> neuer <hi>leaueth vs,</hi> till there be no hope of <hi>amendement.</hi> When the Lord had purpoſed to <hi>deſtroy</hi> the old <hi>world,</hi> becauſe the wickedneſſe thereof was very great, hee did firſt vſe all meanes to <hi>reclaime</hi> them. Hee gaue them an <hi>hundreth</hi> and <hi>twenty</hi> yeeres to <hi>repent</hi> in, and in the <hi>meane while,</hi> ſent <hi>Noah</hi> a Preacher of righteouſnes, to forewarne them of the <hi>danger,</hi> both by <hi>verball</hi> &amp; alſo <hi>viſible</hi> preaching, in making an <hi>Arke,</hi> for the ſauing of himſelfe and his houſhold. <note place="margin">2 Pet 2.5. Heb. 11.7. 2 Sam 15.16. 1 King. 21.18.</note> Hee ſent <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> to <hi>Saul; Elias</hi> to <hi>Ahab; Ionas</hi> to Niniueh, an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to Laodicea: but if <hi>theſe</hi> will not moue, hee caſteth <hi>vtterly</hi> off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laodicea</hi> muſt be <hi>ſpewed out of his mouth.</hi> Her wealthy, inſolent, imperious inhabitants, <hi>father, ſonne, nephew; olde, young,</hi> all muſt be <hi>reiected.</hi> It is not the loſſe of their <hi>wealth</hi> alone, nor decay of <hi>Marchants</hi> and men of <hi>warre,</hi> the <hi>rooting</hi> out of the <hi>nobleſt</hi> families in <hi>Laidicea,</hi> nor the <hi>funerals</hi> of priuate houſes, but the fall of the whole <hi>Citie.</hi> It's a fond <hi>conceit</hi> of the prophane vulgar to make God all of <hi>mercies,</hi> a groſſe <hi>ignorance</hi> to diſioyne mercy and iuſtice in him to whom they are both eſſentiall. Dare wee hope that GOD can be ſo kind to vs as to be vniuſt to <hi>himſelfe?</hi> No, hee will <hi>repay</hi> vengeance to thoſe that will not receiue the call of <hi>mercy. Hee will ſpew them out of his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The <hi>vſe</hi> of this may ſerue as a <hi>glaſſe</hi> to all impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinners, to looke vpon Gods <hi>iudgements,</hi> poured downe vpon them who made no conſcience of their wayes, &amp; neglected his Commandments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:12287:29"/>
Let <hi>worſhippers</hi> of ſtrange Gods looke vpon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſpoyled for this. <note place="margin">Iudg. 2.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>creepers</hi> vnto Images looke vpon <hi>Ieroboam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 14.10.</note> cut off with all his houſe.</p>
            <p>Let raſh <hi>ſwearers</hi> looke vpon the blaſpheming <hi>Sennacherib,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Ki. 19.35.37.</note> King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> killed by his ſons <hi>Adra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi> and <hi>Sharezer,</hi> and an Angell of the Lord ſmiting in his Campe in one night an hundred foureſcore and fiue thouſand.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>prophaners</hi> of the Sabbath looke vpon the <hi>gatherer of ſtickes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 15.36.</note> ſtoned by all the people.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>rebellious</hi> children looke vpon <hi>Abſolon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.9.</note> han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and caſt into a pit.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Murtherers</hi> looke vpon <hi>Cain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.24.</note> his blood was ſhed by <hi>Lamech,</hi> his Nephew.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>adulters</hi> looke vpon foure and twenty <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 25.9.11.</note> periſhing for committing it with the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Moab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>theeues</hi> looke vpon <hi>Achan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 7.24.25.</note> his ſonnes, daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and all his ſubſtance burnt for <hi>ſtealing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let <hi>falſe witneſſes</hi> looke vpon the rulers that accuſed <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.24.</note> they were brought and caſt into the Den of the <hi>Lyons;</hi> they, their children and their wiues, and the Lyons had the maſterie of them, breaking all their bones in pieces, ere euer they came at the ground of the Denne.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>couetous men</hi> looke vpon <hi>Ahab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 22.34.</note> tyrannically poſſeſſing <hi>Naboth</hi> his Vineyard, falling in Battaile.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>luke-warme</hi> profeſſors looke vpon <hi>Laodicea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oroſius.</note> it is fallen by an <hi>Earth-quake</hi> for neglecting the Goſpell. So that as <hi>Chriſt</hi> bad his hearers remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12287:29"/>
               <hi>Lots</hi> wife,<note place="margin">Luk. 17.32.</note> (ſo I may ſay vnto you all) <hi>remember Laodicea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Woe vpon woe is <hi>threatned</hi> againſt <hi>Chorazin, Bethſaida</hi> and <hi>Capernaum,</hi> for their <hi>coldneſſe.</hi> Thoſe Cities glittered with Chriſts <hi>miracles;</hi> their ſtreets ſounded and rang with his <hi>doctrine;</hi> the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants were <hi>priuiledged</hi> with his <hi>familiaritie.</hi> But for as much as there was no more in them then in <hi>Gath,</hi> or <hi>Aſhkelon,</hi> Citties of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and the Vineyard was as barren as the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> and Chriſt was in their <hi>ſtreets,</hi> not in their hearts, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>curſes</hi> were thundred to them; ſo to <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, write it in <hi>tables,</hi> and let it be a monument for the laſt day, that the Lord is <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> towards <hi>vngracious</hi> ſinners, if they quench not his <hi>ſpirit,</hi> if they <hi>deſpiſe</hi> not his <hi>Prophets,</hi> if wee <hi>abuſe</hi> not his <hi>mercies,</hi> if wee <hi>neglect</hi> not his <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, our ſinnes haue made this a <hi>preaching</hi> not fit for theſe times, <hi>bleſsings</hi> muſt ſleepe a while, <hi>mercy</hi> goe aſide, <hi>peace</hi> returne to the God of <hi>peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſ. Lond. in Ionam.</note> and not be ſpoken of. This rather ſhould be our preaching, There is <hi>iudgement</hi> with thee O Lord, with thee there is <hi>ruine,</hi> and <hi>ſubuerſion,</hi> with thee is <hi>battaile,</hi> and <hi>famine,</hi> and <hi>ſnares, plague,</hi> and <hi>ſtorme</hi> and <hi>tempeſt, fire</hi> and <hi>brimſtone,</hi> therefore thou ſhalt be feared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> are two ſiſters, and as the one hath had her day, ſo the other ſhal not miſſe hers, vnleſſe we be zealous and amended. The Lord hath two armes, two cups, two recompences, and doubtleſſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12287:30"/>there is a <hi>reward</hi> for the <hi>righteous,</hi> and <hi>torment</hi> for the <hi>obſtinate,</hi> and <hi>falſe-hearted,</hi> and <hi>luke-warme</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor. Which ſhould be a <hi>motiue</hi> to all <hi>true-harted</hi> Proteſtants, to ioyne together as one man, <hi>againſt</hi> them that haue euill will at <hi>Syon,</hi> the common <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary</hi> the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and all that are <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> the <hi>Gangrens</hi> of this Land, if euer wee would haue <hi>good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All <hi>Iſrael</hi> was againſt <hi>Athan,</hi> in the Valley of <hi>Achor,</hi> becauſe hee was the cauſe that they could not ſtand againſt their enemies. In the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> againſt <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> there were no fewer, by report, then foure and twenty <hi>daggers</hi> ſtabd into his body, becauſe he was taken by the <hi>Nobilitie</hi> of Rome, to be an <hi>enemie</hi> to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; ſhall <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> be ſuffred to runne from <hi>houſe</hi> to <hi>houſe,</hi> and ſeduce whole <hi>fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies?</hi> ſhall we nurſe vp <hi>Lyons-whelpes</hi> for our owne ouerthrow? What ſaftie can we be in, when ſuch <hi>Miſcreants</hi> lurke in your <hi>dewllings?</hi> iet in your <hi>ſtreetes?</hi> when neither <hi>Country,</hi> nor <hi>Citie,</hi> nor <hi>Court</hi> is free of theſe <hi>conſpiratours,</hi> keeping a dayly <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> of all our actions, and haue <hi>taken to vſe</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath beene ſpoken, or done, againſt them, theſe many <hi>Halcyon</hi> yeeres of ours, meaning to <hi>exchange</hi> it, tenne for one, if euer they ſee the <hi>day</hi> of their long <hi>expected toleration,</hi> and ſo <hi>expulſion</hi> of the Goſpell: which Lord let them neuer ſee.</p>
            <p>The gates of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot hurt vs, no nor the gates of <hi>Hell</hi> vnleſſe we hurt our ſelues.</p>
            <p>I appeale to <hi>you Worthy,</hi> and Honourable
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12287:30"/>
               <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> to whom the ſword of <hi>iuſtice</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. You may thus reaſon, as the Oratour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Catiline.</hi> Did <hi>Publius Scipio</hi> a priuate man kill <hi>Tiberius Gracchus,</hi> but lightly weakning the ſtate of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and ſhall we that are conſuls let <hi>Catiline</hi> alone deſirous to lay waſt all the world with ſlaughterings and <hi>fierings?</hi> Not onely for Gods ſake, but for our <hi>Kings ſake,</hi> whoſe deputies ye are, as he is Gods; not onely for <hi>Religion,</hi> but for very <hi>pollicie,</hi> as you regard the peace of this <hi>ſtate,</hi> and well-farre of the <hi>Church,</hi> as you loue your owne liues, rouze vp your <hi>ſpirits;</hi> the cauſe is the Lords, vindicate his diſhonour. He hath made our <hi>Land</hi> a <hi>ſanctuary</hi> for true Religion, a <hi>refuge</hi> and ſhade in the heate of the day, for perſecuted <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors,</hi> who haue beene chaſed like <hi>Bees</hi> from their owne <hi>Hiues.</hi> Hee hath made this place a <hi>Temple</hi> for himſelfe to <hi>dwell</hi> in; the zeale of it hath beene <hi>famous</hi> ouer the world: O let it not be a common <hi>receit</hi> for all commers, <hi>Atheiſts, Neuters, Hypocrits, luke-warme Profeſſors, Popiſh wanderers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the <hi>defence</hi> of Religion, that made <hi>Dauid, Salomon, Ioſias, Conſtantine, Edward</hi> the 6 Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and our late bleſſed Prince <hi>Henry</hi> ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, that their names amongſt all true hearted <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> are like a precious oyntment, their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance is ſweet as hony, <note place="margin">Eccl. 49.1.</note> and as Muſicke at a banquet of wine. It is this that muſt honour you all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember,</hi> that to whom much is giuen, of them much ſhall be required. Wee of this Land haue beene a <hi>long time</hi> the trees of the <hi>Lords Vineyard,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:12287:31"/>full of ſappe, of as many <hi>fauours</hi> as any people of the <hi>world.</hi> If we be his <hi>Oliue-trees,</hi> we muſt haue fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If his <hi>Figge-trees,</hi> we muſt haue ſweetneſſe. If his <hi>Vine-trees,</hi> we muſt haue Wine, chearing the heart; I meane, we muſt bring <hi>forth</hi> good fruit to benefit others.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Heathens</hi> faine of the <hi>Powers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> Dial.</note> that euery one choſe a tree. <hi>Iupiter,</hi> he choſe the <hi>Oake</hi> for <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; Neptune,</hi> the <hi>Cedar</hi> for <hi>tallneſſe; Apollo,</hi> the <hi>Laurell</hi> for <hi>greenneſſe; Venus,</hi> the <hi>Poplar</hi> for <hi>white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Pallas,</hi> the <hi>Vine</hi> for <hi>fruitfulneſſe:</hi> our true GOD hath <hi>choſen</hi> vs as a <hi>peculiar people</hi> to himſelfe. O then, bring forth <hi>fruits, worthy</hi> of the Goſpell: be <hi>earneſt</hi> and <hi>diligent</hi> to make your <hi>Election ſure,</hi> eſpecially you, whom the Lord hath placed as the <hi>Eye of this Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus</hi> tolde <hi>Aſclepius</hi> that <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt</hi> was the Image of <hi>Heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 8. ciu. 23.</note> I am ſure your <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> is an Image of the <hi>whole earth,</hi> and I hope it ſhall be called <hi>Vrbs aterna,</hi> an euerlaſting Citie, more truely then euer <hi>Rome</hi> was by <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pind. <hi>Od.</hi>
               </note> though <hi>I know it muſt haue a period.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which <hi>Pindarus</hi> fained of the Cittie <hi>Rhodes</hi> is true amongſt you; <hi>Gold</hi> hath beene as <hi>plentifull</hi> as if it had almoſt <hi>rained</hi> downe from Heauen: <hi>gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things are ſpoken of this Citie of God:</hi> it hath the <hi>Temple</hi> of the Lord, and <hi>Court</hi> of the Kings ſeates of <hi>Indgement.</hi> It hath a <hi>Royall Nauy</hi> of Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and is fenced not onely with theſe wals of wood as <hi>Gracia</hi> was againſt <hi>Xerxes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herod. Poly.</note> but it hath a Tower furniſhed with Inſtruments of <hi>braſſe</hi> and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12287:31"/>
               <hi>Iron,</hi> againſt your enemies, it hath many ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>buildings,</hi> and faithfull <hi>Watch-men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.2.</note> yet vnleſſe the Lord keepe the <hi>Citie,</hi> the watch-man waketh but in vaine. Defend <hi>Religion,</hi> and the Lord will fight for you, and defend you all.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake to you <hi>aged Fathers;</hi> Be like the Sunne in the <hi>Firmament;</hi> not like <hi>Ezechias</hi> Sun that went backeward, not like <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> Sunne that ſtood ſtill; but <hi>Dauids</hi> Sunne, that like a Bridegroome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out of his Chamber, and as a Champion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth to runne his race. Be like the Sunne in the <hi>Firmament,</hi> more glorious at the ſetting then ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: the neerer you are to your graues, be the more zealous in good workes.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake to you <hi>young men;</hi> Beloued <hi>brethren,</hi> offer to God the firſt fruits of your youth, call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of the Lord for helpe: be ſtrong in defence of that profeſſion, wherein you were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, and hee that hath begunne in you a good worke will perfect it.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake to you <hi>Matrons</hi> and deuout <hi>Virgins;</hi> Learne of <hi>Eſther</hi> and her <hi>hand-maides,</hi> to be true to the Lord and his word, ſo ſhall all <hi>generations</hi> call you bleſſed.</p>
            <p>In a word, I ſpeake to you <hi>All;</hi> Remember what you haue <hi>heard:</hi> many <hi>Preachers</hi> haue beene ſent vnto vs. The <hi>Heauens</hi> ouer our heads, haue beene reſolued into teares, weeping for our ſinnes. The <hi>Earth</hi> vnder our feete, hath trembled for feare of thoſe plagues which we deſerue. The roaring <hi>Sea</hi> hath ouer-ſwelled the vſuall bounds. <hi>Death,</hi> hath
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12287:32"/>beene ſometimes vſherd amongſt you, with the pale horſe of a ranging Peſtilence, deſtroying day and night. <hi>O let not theſe things be forgotten, as though they had neuer beene!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the laſt, let the reward moue vs, Behold this day CHRIST ſtandeth and <hi>knocketh</hi> at the dore of <hi>your</hi> hearts, ſaying; <hi>If any man heare my voyce, and open the dore, I will come in vnto him, and</hi> banquet <hi>with him, and hee with mee.</hi> This knocking is his <hi>calling</hi> vnto vs by his <hi>words, workes, benefits.</hi> This dore is the cloſet of our <hi>hearts;</hi> the hearing, is our <hi>obeying;</hi> the <hi>opening,</hi> is the <hi>readineſſe</hi> of our ſoules; this <hi>comming in vnto vs,</hi> is his <hi>being</hi> in vs by his holy Spirit; this <hi>banquetting</hi> is the continuall feaſt of a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which that wee may all haue, and ſo ſit with CHRIST in his <hi>Throne,</hi> when we haue <hi>ouer come;</hi> the good Lord for his mercies ſake grant it to <hi>whom,</hi> with the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> that <hi>Trinitie</hi> in <hi>Vnitie,</hi> and <hi>Vnitie</hi> in <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> be aſcribed all <hi>praiſe</hi> and <hi>power, glory</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe, dignitie</hi> and <hi>dominion,</hi> this day, and for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12287:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
